Heat. Heat.
Heat.
Hey, Heat.
Hello, good evening, good day everybody
and welcome back to the Ask a Bidget
show. Today we are doing episode 330 and
I'm going to take questions from the
comments. Questions you have asked in
the comments about geopolitics and
history. Before we get into that, let me
see who is who is there on the live
chat. Before I do that, uh just a brief
announcement. The next live stream
episode 331 will not happen tomorrow. It
will happen on Monday 8:00 p.m. India
time. Tomorrow as some of you may know
there is an India Pakistan cricket match
around the same time and if I do the
live stream at that time I suppose very
few people will watch. I have tried in
the past it doesn't work so so I'm
moving I have moved it to Monday 8:00
p.m. Okay. Uh let's see who is there on
the live chat. Akshai Bharadwaj Ice
Gulim is very excited. Good to see you.
High schoolm 1055
chess pro 11 anuman mahapatra dana priya
football baktitra
clearly
someone with that name. Okay. Aravsha,
Zubon, Eizen, Geopolitical Dubai from
Indor, Gajapat from Odisha, SKR7733.
Uh, Gora TV, The Strummer A1 1989, Reika
Humbl Ju.
Uh, who else? Admi, Rishuk, Talugdar,
Hulor, Kiki, Kiki, Susant, good morning
to you. Good morning. Uh, G TV once
again. Real Vadimir Putin, Ram Ram G. Um
Tadas Namaste Prasad Abdalal.
Okay. Yeah. Hi McLean 69. Good evening.
Uh Kahan hello. U who else? Who else are
you saying? Pranam Sergi. Panam to you.
Dic Shrian. Namaste. Ashish Chabra.
Namaste G. Brave robot. Meow in in
Devanagri. Okay. Uh Nagarand Shana is
here from Hyderabad. Good evening sir.
Anandpai namaskar. John M. Funk namaste.
Bam. Edits 12:47.
Good to see you, sir. Good to see you.
Anime Paratia's daughter says, "Hello."
Well, hello to your daughter, sir.
Hello. Good to see you. Uh, Mahabu
Shetty, good evening, ma'am. I'm good.
How are you doing? Uh, Brave Robot is
cooking dinner. Well, Brave Robot is
cooking dinner. I hope it's tasty and
is good. Yeah. Uh meets mystery. Namaste
online. Har mahadev
tesh pandemi once again. Kahan Obear
hello good to see you sir. Uh online
once again Shandi Chandani Priya good
evening ma'am. Krishna of the Surum
Netherlands. Good good afternoon sir.
Good afternoon Alvin Rodriguez. Hello
wise idiot. Good to see you.
Okay Anu. Uh who else do we have? Mahita
Bushetti J Krishna indeed. Tushar
Kalborgi good to see you. Namaste.
General Subutai, hello. Hello. Mitri
once again back after a long time. Good
to have you, sir. Good to have you
always. This is Hushkapur. Good evening.
Kamal Parasher from Merit UP. Good to
see you, sir. Vihank Kuran, good to see
you as well. Uh, who else? Who else? Uh,
Mac 4 J1U, good to see you. Namaste.
Rahul Kumar. Rakkesh Mistri is here from
Bangladesh. Good evening, sir. Namaskar.
Namaskar. Darren Patil is here from
Mahashri. Happy Mah to everybody in
advance. Anand pai no emotions left.
Okay. Um and so many other people.
Manisha namaste. Ansley Franco. Hello.
Rakkesh Misti once again. Kahan and the
strummer.
Rahul Dunak. Good evening. Namaste G.
Viprit. Viprit. Good to see you. Vrit
Arjun is here from Siliguri. Well, good
evening to you. Rahul Hintani is here
from Mumbai. Random skull. Jri Krishna.
M41
J1U says I don't watch India Pakistan
matches. Well, good for you, sir. Good
for you. PG Dhland is here from Dohlan,
Germany. Well, good evening. Uh good
afternoon to you and thank you for the
kind words. Uh who else do we have? We
we're going to have a lot of people
obviously uh I won't be able to greet
you all. Meet Bri, Krishna Sharma,
Ujasit Kumar,
uh Cast Jana, Kastana, Rahul Sanjjo,
Sanjay Mukji is here from Shanghai. Good
evening. Uh good uh yeah good night I
suppose almost parak parakala is here
from Miami good morning chess pro rahad
g um
so many people okay so uh I won't be
able to greet you all individually as
always but uh let's see we we I'll take
questions from the live chat not from
the live chat from the comments but I
saw a couple of questions in the live
chat so let me take a couple of those
just before I begin I where are these
where are these at the very beginning I
suppose
So, um,
one second. Where did we have it? I saw
something somewhere. Yes, Zubon isn't
says, "Long time." Well, long time. Good
to have you. There's a problem going on
in Nagaland between the Nagas and the
cookies right now. Can you please
analyze it for us? And SKR says, "The
way things are going, I think soon I
will need to say good evening from Impal
Cookand."
So uh I'm not sure if the media is
reporting much about what's happening in
Manipur, Nagal and that area. Uh but um
well yeah what we are seeing here is
what we are seeing is what's happening.
So um um Zubonis wants me to analyze
what's happening. I have analyzed this
in detail. I mean the root causes and
all that. uh so the the core issue is
that this region of the far eastern
region of India the Manalipur Nagaland
region it's on the border between India
and Burma I mean let's take a look at
the map okay give me a second I'll put
it on the map
it's on the border it's it's a border
region and uh to the east we have Burma
Manipur and Nagalan both and in this
part of Burma there's a there's a group
of I mean there's this group of uh
tribals you know various tribal
ethnicities who collectively have been
given the the name cookies by the
British and who are not Indian, who are
not even Burmese
and they have infiltrated in very large
numbers in in parts of large parts of
large areas of Manipur and so on and
uh the British brought them into India
as a punishment for the uh Manipuri
kings who fought against the British the
Mate Hindu kings. Um and in 1900 the
number of cookies in Manipur was like
measly like maybe a th00and 2,000 or
whatever. I see the you can check out
the British census records but today
it's lacks and lacks in the past 10 or
so years 10 15 20 years several lakhs
have infiltrated across the open border
into Manipur and they have taken over
very large parts of Manipur territory.
These are all foreigners. But the moment
they come into India, they acquire
documents
and uh they say that we have been here
forever. Then we are the original
inhabitants. The mates are outsiders.
That's sort of nonsense they say. And in
the 1980s and 1990s, especially in the
1990s, the cookies went to war against
the Nagas. The Nagas are also an
indigenous ethnic group in the region.
The mates and the Nagas are the
indigenous people of Manipur and
Nagaland.
The cookies are foreigners. In the
1990s, the cookies went to war against
the nagas and there were these massive
clashes
and the cookies were given shelter for
some reason by the mates to to calm
things down. Yeah. And now 2023 onwards,
the cookies have gone to war against the
mates and they've done horrific
atrocities, absolute terrorism. And now
that the mates have been subdued with
the help possibly of the Indian
government who has disarmed them. See in
the northeast of India, the far east of
India from the 1950s onwards, every
state had multiple ethn uh insurgencies.
The government of India gave horrific
step stepmotherly treatment to all these
states. So everybody wanted to be out of
India. Everybody went insurgent in every
state whether it is Misoramid, whether
it is Nagaland, whether it is Assam,
whether it is Manipur, whether it is
whatever the state, you had multiple
insurgences and multiple ethnic groups.
So Manipur also had multiple ethnic
groups. So the Matey ethnic groups have
been disarmed now mostly by the
government of India. But the cookies are
fully armed
and now they're going to war against
against the Nagas.
The cookies will not stop until they
have taken everything over. And for some
reason the government of India seems to
be okay with this for some reason.
Whatever it is. So uh now that the mates
have been confined to this little part
of Manipur,
now the cookies are going after the
Nagas. That's what's happening right
now. I'm not sure if the media is
covering this. So it looks like cookie
land for Christ is happening. And see
it's not a religious issue. The Nagas
are themselves now all mostly converted
to Christianity. The cookies claim to be
Christian. Sometimes they claim to be
Jews even though they eat pork. But now
they're going to war against the Nagas.
I'm I suppose it from the government of
India's perspective this may serve some
kind of geopolitical interest. I don't
I'm not sure what the interests are. I
fail to see it. Maybe there is some you
know master stroke calculation somewhere
perhaps. So that's what's happening. So
the cookies are now going to war against
the Nagas Christian on Christian.
Um so it looks like cookie land has
already happened.
If you see the visuals coming out on
social media in places like Churachpur,
you have these big mobs of cookie
terrorists armed with automatic rifles
or who are shouting and screaming and
jumping and dancing and playing music
and fighting each other
and setting in other parts of Manipur
setting fire to the houses of various uh
uh Naga people, Naga villages. So it
looks like Kukiland has already
happened. It's a de facto separate
administration, de facto separate
country. You don't see any Indian armed
forces or Indian government officials
anywhere in these videos.
So cookie land for Christ has happened.
I would not say that India has full
sovereignty or Manipur anymore. That's
the situation.
Okay. Now let's go get going with uh
with with the questions I have chosen
from the comments.
Right. Okay. uh many people wanted to uh
me to discuss the trade deal. I mean I
discussed it last week. Uh first of all
let's okay let's see the questions.
Abisha says the US has changed the deal
slightly in India's favor. Do you think
India demanded it? Rush says the US
released a fact sheet and then changed
it. India commits to India intents. So
the joint statement between India and
the US which was put out by the um by
the Indian government
said that India intends to purchase $500
billion of US products within a certain
time frame and the American statement
said that India has committed to
purchasing that. So that's a pressure
tactic. That's the you know putting this
this falsehood out in public. The
intention was to then make India postf
facto accept this this change. So India
has stood firm and now it has the
Americans have changed it back to India
intents in instead of India commits
pulses clause. The Americans had
introduced some pulses clause that was
never agreed upon. Uh data security tax
etc all those things. So yeah, the
Americans have tried all these
backhanded maneuvers and all these
pressure tactics and all these underhand
tactics, all these arm twisting
maneuvers and methods.
So let's understand one thing very
clearly my friends. This trade deal it's
an interim framework for it's it's a
framework for an inter interim trade
deal. So an interim trade deal is not a
final trade deal. It's a temporary thing
and what has been announced is a
framework for an inter interim trade
deal. So it's not even a deal. It's just
a framework.
So understand this, any deal with the US
is not worth the paper it is written on.
Trump will go and change it tomorrow
morning. Trump will walk out of the deal
if he feels like. Trump does that,
doesn't he? Trump walked out recently of
the deal he signed with South Korea.
Trump in the past has walked away from
deal that was signed by the US with Iran
the JCPOA the joint comprehensive plan
of action in 2017 or whatever it was the
US habitually walks out of deals it has
signed
so understand I don't know why certain
people are celebrating this trade deal
with the US even politicians are
celebrating it in certain political
parties there's nothing to celebrate
here this is a framework for a temporary
interim trade trade deal which is not
even the final thing and this is a
framework and the moment the framework
was announced the Americans started you
know post factor changing it
so there is nothing to c celebrate here
if things stand as they are they are
okay it's not a terribly bad deal for
India it's actually in in a variety of
ways better than the deals the Americans
have given to their own allies okay
let's not compare with Bangladesh for on
one or two points not important and if
you see the drill down into the points
you will see there is no comparison at
So overall it's a decent thing. It's a
it's a if if it actually stands then
it's actually a good deal for India comp
compared to what the Americans have
given to their allies. It's obviously
not an equal deal but the Americans
aren't treated treating anybody equally.
Right? So overall it's it's good
relative to everything else the
Americans are doing. Uh but once again
my my word of caution is that no deal
signed with the Americans is worth the
paper they signed on. The Americans will
anytime at any given point in time if
they feel like it, they will tear it up
and walk away. So nothing to celebrate
over here as far as I see it.
Okay. Next.
Real Vladimir Putin says, "What is the
update in the Russia India relationship?
Is India falling into the American
camp?" Omisha says Russian deputy deputy
foreign minister says hopes India Russia
ties won't suffer and USA is trying to
ban India. Maybe Russia is worried that
India may slowly reduce its oil imports.
Also India exits a Russia backed Mali
lithium project. Has the US secured a
geopolitical victory? Will Delhi Moscow
relations suffer?
Look what does the US want from India?
The US wants
India bending the need. The US wants
India becoming their vasal. That's what
the Americans want. It's plain and
clear. Plain and simple. No question
about it. India does not want to become
anyone's vasal. So India is resisting
this. Okay. India is resisting. The
Americans are pushing for this. So what
is the situation? India has recently
gone ahead like we discussed and signed
this framework for an intering trade
deal with the US. And the terms we have
secured are reasonably good compared to
what other US allies have secured. So
it's overall good. But what did we have
to give up in exchange? One thing is
Chabahar. We have walked out of it. It
looks like we have liquidated our stake
in the Chabahar port, paid the money to
Iran and walked out. It looks like Yeah,
that's one thing. The secondly, it looks
like the Americans are insisting that
India will not buy any more Russian oil
and the Trump the White House put out a
different set of different documents in
which clause 4 or something says that
the US will set up a monitoring
situation that will monitor India's
activities and if if India resumes any
kind of purchase of Russian oil whether
it is direct or indirect then the
Americans will reimpose 25% tariffs on
India. So I'm not sure if this was
agreed upon in the trade deal. Maybe
this is something that's external to the
trade deal. But the Americans once again
are using their leverage upon us and
they are insisting that India will not
buy Russian oil anymore. Now, now the
question is the Indian government is in
a dilemma. This was not part of the
trade deal possibly because the joint
statement says nothing about Russian
oil. So, it looks like this was not part
of the trade deal, but the Americans are
putting it in through the back door,
through something that's external to the
trade deal that they're going to set up
a monitoring uh situation, whatever
monitoring center. They'll monitor
Indian activities. Who the hell are
they? They are the hedgemon of the
world. They are the superpower. They can
do it. That's the hell who the hell they
are, right? So, they will do If you if
India purchases even one tanker worth of
Russian oil, then 25% tariffs back on
India. So that puts India into a very
tough situation. What does India do? One
thing India can do is stop purchasing
Russian oil. But then you lose your
so-called strategic autonomy and it's
not exactly vasal hood but it's one step
along the road to becoming a vasal. It's
it's one step. It's not all the way. But
once you start accepting external
pressures as to what you will do,
you know, before the 2024 election,
parliamentary election, general
election, Prime Minister Modi had had
given a bunch of interviews, right, to
various uh media outlets. In one of
these interviews, Prime Minister Modi
had said that whatever happens, India
does not accept thirdparty pressure or
third party directions as to what to do
in any bilateral relationship. So let's
say we have a relationship with let's
say India and Russia we will not accept
any third party instructions as to how
to behave like US instructions that's
that's the kind of thing he had said and
here if India actually agrees to what
the Americans are insisting then that
independence clearly is gone and now we
are
even in Chabahar the Americans are
insisting we stop playing the game so we
we have pulled out once again the
Americans are deciding what we do so we
are kind of not bending the knee
completely, not caving in completely,
but we are kind of bowing down to a
little to a small extent then you know
what maybe it's a temporary thing. Maybe
we'll do it for a while and maybe we
will hide our strength and bing shopping
said said for China. So that's a valid
strategy in geopolitics. when you are
weak, you show that you're weak and yes
sir, we will do what you say but don't
give up the core red lines of your
strategic autonomy and sovereignty. So
uh so what's the update on the India
relationship? It it remains to be seen.
I think the Russians are concerned.
The Russians have offered various things
to India. They've offered the Sukoy 57.
I'm not sure if it's the best aircraft.
Maybe the Rafal is a good idea. I'm not
sure if the Rafal deal is the best deal
or maybe it is. I don't know. But the
Russians wanted India to go for the
Sukoy 57. We've had issues with Russian
equipment in the past with the MiG 29s
and maybe even the Sukoy 30s, you know,
availability of spares and the engine
serviceability issues and so on. So
maybe the Rafal may be actually a better
deal compared to the Sukoy 57. Even the
the Russians operate only 20 or so Sukoy
57s. So if it's something the Russians
have adopted in large numbers, then we
will be confident it's a good plane. So
there are issues. So that's why we have
gone for the Rafal. The Russians
obviously would have preferred we buy
their aircraft. They were apparently
offering full technology transfer but
once again we have faced issue with
issues with the Russia in the past
regarding these things whether it is
aircraft carriers, whether it is fighter
planes and other things. So one has to
be careful right. Um overall I would say
the India Russia relationship is very
important for India. India can't afford
to you know jump into the American lap
into the American camp and abandon
Russia doesn't make sense for India to
do that u of course the US pressure will
be intense it's the pressure will be
felt by our officials behind the scenes
it will not be visible to us uh Mali
lithium project also there is this issue
right is there an American angle in
there as well so
if this continues if this pattern
continues then perhaps India India
Russia relations may suffer
right um if India genuinely stops
purchasing Russian oil it doesn't look
like we have done that so far but if we
are not doing that then we will see 25%
tariffs being slapped back upon us very
soon so we'll have to see if tariffs
aren't slapped by Donald Trump 25% on
India then it means that India has
actually stopped purchasing Russian oil
which will be a significant concession
to the Americans and it will of course
be a setback for Russia.
It will also be to some extent a setback
to India Russia relations, right? Uh so
I think it it's still too early to say
whether the Americans have secured this
geopolitical victory of forcing India to
stop purchasing Russian oil the way they
have forced in the past India to stop
buying Venezuelan oil in 2010 or
thereabouts and later Iranian oil. Have
they now forced NATO to stop buying
Russian oil? If they have, then it's a
significant setback for India and for
Russia and for India Russia relations. I
think we need to wait and watch. It's
too early to uh pass judgment on on this
matter. But it looks like
at least some of their pressure is
having an effect on India. So let's see.
Too early to say.
Okay. Mali, right? Sam Panic says,
"After the Bhat US trade deal, we are
getting signs of Bhat gradually reducing
its crude oil imports from Russia and
recently Bat exited from Russianbacked
lithium project in Mali due to security
reasons. Is Barat now slowly caving into
American demands? What's your thought on
this matter?" Miran Kasikar Biswar says,
"After India pulled out of the Russia
backed lithium project in Mali over
security concerns, are we being pushed
towards choosing sides? And from a
purely self-interested self standpoint,
should India leverage its massive market
the way China does to extract deeper
technology transfers, defense
partnerships and better market access
from Russia? Real brother Putin says
what's the possibility of us India
becoming a US. The government of India
has already helped us in Manipur. In the
case of Starling, they are digging their
own grave. Even if they are not on
foreign payroll, they are making sure
that the potential regime change in
India by US in the future becomes easy
for Americans. So what's going on?
So this Mali situation. So India has
couple of days ago the news came out
that India has pulled out of uh of this
uh project Russia backed lithium project
in Mali citing securities the security
isn't great and so on. I mean Russia is
there Russia is not worried about
security. How come India is worried
about it? India also one angle one
possibility is that India has also
discovered its own massive lithium uh
reserves in various parts of India why
not develop those instead of going and
working in Mali but if you work in Mali
with the Russians then you have access
to you know resources from that that
part of the world from that part of
Africa which obviously gives you options
it it it's called diversification right
so it makes sense to do that but India
has pulled out of that so has that
happened under American pressure it's
possible it is indeed possible see
If if it's not happened under American
pressure, it's because of security
reasons. In in that case, it shows that
India has no appetite for risk.
Geopolitically, you need to have an
appetite for risk. The Russians have an
appetite for risk. They take big risks
in sending their uh paramilitary forces
etc. in in various parts of Africa.
There are casualties, there are
setbacks, right? These things happen.
Your people die sometimes. But the
nation as a whole, Russia, it it takes
risks, right? China also takes risks.
Not to the extent that Russia does. So
Russia, it is the muscle and China is
the money. That's the relationship in
Africa.
India could I mean it makes sense for
India to also be involved in Africa. But
if India has genuinely done this for
security reasons where it's it's
strange. I mean we can send our own our
own troops if required, right?
or a paramilitary force not the official
Indian armed forces or depend on Russian
security which is usually good. So I'm
not sure what's happened. If it is
because of American pressure, then once
again we are kind of on the road slowly
towards a situation where we could
potentially be called a US wasal in the
future. Not right now. Right? So and and
maybe it's American pressure and maybe
it's it's a strategic choice we've taken
right now. Right now we are not strong
enough. Let's pull back. That also is a
valid choice. It doesn't mean we areal
today. But if this continues over and
over again if there's a pattern that
just goes in a certain direction for a
long period of time for a for a in a
consistent manner that's when you start
becoming a vasal gradually slowly right
now it's not the case but yeah it's
concerning to some extent at least um
yeah so is bat slowly caving into US
demands
looks like there are there are some
indications that to some extent we are
accepting American demands it looks like
possibly can't say for sure but it looks
like that I mean there are no
coincidences in geopolitics right
pulling out of chabahar
this Mali thing uh the US removing the
25% tariffs on India for purchasing
Russian oil and setting up monitoring of
India if India resumes the purchase of
Russian oil all these things form a
pattern at least three data points we
have let's see if more data points
emerge we'll see about that so looks
like we are accepting some US demands
possibly but that doesn't mean that we
are a vasal right now if this continues
and it crosses certain lines then you
can say we are on the road to washood
but yeah you can say this is the first
steps in that direction it doesn't mean
we are that um Manipur yeah we discussed
Manipur Manipur is a disaster we don't
have any more full sovereignty of
Manipur in my opinion okay Starlink I am
have been very clear from the very
beginning India should not allow
Starlink to operate in India but looks
like we are doing exactly what I have
been saying not to do. So we'll see it's
still not operational in India but uh
looks like we are going in that
direction. I hope not. Um
and there are all the various internal
issues in India and so on. So yeah
you know these are those those times in
the world when everything seems tough
but that's that's where we are.
Okay. RPPL says do you think India is
doing bad in Jew politics because first
India doesn't make any irreversible harm
to terrorist nation Pakistan during
operation zindur and also did not get
any territorial gains Bangladesh is out
of hand to oppose it in in opposite
Indra Gandhi separated Pakistan and
Bangladesh so the question is why is
India not doing well in geopolitics
right I mean for some time for a for a
few years it was all about the rise of
India and all that Right. India is now
respected across the world. When you
travel abroad, people see you with
respect. And and that was a story for a
while, wasn't it? And now it looks like
everything is going backwards, right? So
what's the situation? See, I am a
realistic person. I am not a
sensationalist. I don't sensationalize
things like very lots of YouTubers do.
you know all those world whenever I go
to uh def to uh as a guest on a podcast
typically I discuss the things I discuss
here but you will see that the title and
thumbnail is a lot world war II that
sort of thing so that is called
sensationalism
I don't do sensationalism at least here
on this channel I don't do it anywhere
else but yeah the title and thumbnail
that other people put up it's not in my
control the point is I am realistic and
let's discuss this realistically is
India doing well in geopolitics and is
India poorly in geopolitics. I think
it's middle ground somewhere. India
isn't doing great in geopolitics.
India isn't doing great overall but
India is still growing as an economy.
India has a lot that's going in its
favor. But India has issues.
India has various issues. So I always
discuss things from the perspective of
hard power, power projection, military
bases, GDP and so on. Let's discuss
things from a geoeconomic perspective,
shall we? Hm. So where does India stand
in terms of see the most powerful
countries in the world? They control a
number of things in the world or in some
parts of the world at least. They
control resources.
Resources are the key to everything in
geopolitics. They're the key to power.
Okay? They control resources. Then they
control
or own manufacturing.
You take those raw materials, raw
resources, natural resources and turn
them into finished products. That
happens through manufacturing. So you
have resources and you have
manufacturing. Then to do manufacturing
you need human capital. You need
highquality human beings. Okay? You need
intellectual property, the knowhow, the
technology to convert these raw
materials into finished products.
Right? Human capital. It's intellectual
property. It is technology. So you have
resources, you have manufacturing, you
have human capital, intellectual
property and technology. Then and
knowledge, knowledge the knowhow of how
to do things and then at the end of the
day you need money. Your GDP matters,
right? What's your GDP? How much are you
earning and how much what's your gross
domestic produce and so on. So where
does India stand in all of this? India
is not I mean India is a massive land
area, right? subcontinent sized thing
land area. So we have plenty of
resources but we don't have the kind of
resources that Russia has or Africa has
as a whole. We lack certain natural
resources such as oil and gas. We depend
on other countries for our energy
requirements. Right? We uh import oil
and gas from various other nations. We
are not self-sufficient in terms of
energy. We are not energy sovereign.
uh other resources for example file
material uranium we have to import from
other countries right um
we produce most of our own food and so
on so when it comes to resources the
critical things we kind of lack when it
comes to rare earths and lithium and all
we have big resources but we don't use
them so you see that that
that is a lack of strength that's a lack
of initiative lack of whatever but it
makes you weaker compared to nations who
actually use the resources they have
then manufacturing Well, where are we on
manufacturing? What happened to make in
India? It's going okay. It's not 10 out
of 10. It's not 0 out of 10. It's maybe
five out of 10, right? It's not doing
great, but it's not doing very poorly
also. Maybe five out of 10. But China is
like 9.8 out of 10 in terms of
manufacturing. The Chinese have done
their job. The Chinese also have this
lack of resources at least in terms of
energy. But manufacturing, they have
mastered it. Human capital, they have
really improved the human capital
through the education system and through
training. They they're they're citizens
in uh science and technology and
manufacturing and all that engineering
all that they have acquired all the
intellectual intellectual property they
need the all the technology they need
all the knowledge the knowhow they need
India lags far behind in in China than
China in these matters so resources
India lacks resources manufacturing
India is not doing great manufacturing
we haven't solved our problems human
capital abysmal poor ridiculously bad
trashy education system technology we
still beg for technology knowledge and
knowhow it's all going out brain drain
right when it comes to GDP we're doing
okay but we are like 1/4 of China one I
don't know what of the US so very fourth
largest GDP in the world but relatively
quite small so these are the issues why
India is doing poorly in geopolitics
okay it's not just about military
strength it's not just about how many
nukes you have from a military
perspective the air force force while
India's air force is just slightly ahead
of the the Pakistani air force. Can you
believe it?
I just don't understand how we have
reached the situation,
right? Uh we still import things. We
still import Rafals. We've signed a huge
deal with the French for Rafals.
Missiles, we have some of the best
missiles in the world. I I hope we have
adequate numbers of missiles. Maybe tens
of thousands of missiles we would need
to fight a proper sustained war. I hope
we have that. I'm not sure. But let's
see. Uh navy wise we are on u we have
embarked upon a ship building uh
campaign which is good maybe 50 warships
are being constructed right now all
right uh we are lagging behind terribly
in submarines right power projection
well we can't project power even in the
subcontinent the external powers can do
region changes around us all around us
east Pakistan west Pakistan Nepal etc we
just sit and watch so we can't even
project power in our own neighborhood in
our own backyard right forget about the
Indian Ocean region. The Indian Ocean
region is our strategic backyard. That's
our slogan. But what do we actually do
for it to make it happen? Uh maybe we
are kind of working on that. But yeah,
the navy naval power is is key to that.
Uh we are essentially out of the space
race now. The government doesn't seem to
think that space is important when
everybody else is going to the moon and
then to Mars and also in Earth orbit.
But we have simply given up it looks
like the space race. And then we have
internal issues in India.
I mean you must have heard me say that
the Americans when they talk about India
their relationship with India they they
speak about shared shared values that
India and the US have shared values but
when the Americans talk about Pakistan
they talk about shared interests that
the US and Pakistan have shared
interests well interests always trump
values
do we all do we Indians 1.4 4 billion
Indians. Do we have shared values? Do we
have shared interests?
Well, the way things are going,
different groups have different
interests and different values now. And
different groups are being pitted
against each other
within the country. So when this
happens, you're going to have internal
divisions. The internal divisions were
originally created by the Turks and then
by the British. But now we are
exacerbating that. we are deepening and
widening the the the the divisions of
the fissures. That's what we are doing.
So these are the reasons why India is
doing not so great in geopolitics. You
see it's not about Pakistan and the
terrorist nation and operation Sindur
and obviously all that is also there.
These are symptoms not the actual root
causes you see.
So yeah that's a realistic view
of where India stands in geopolitics.
Real Vladimir Putin says what makes the
US so powerful that it can intervene
militarily anywhere without damaging its
economy. Swami says why does the US have
so advanced power projection
capabilities? China and Russia also have
very strong militaries and are neck in
multiple military technologies. Is power
projection mostly dependent on military
bases overseas? So why is the US so
powerful? It can intervene militarily
anywhere without damaging its economy.
Well, it doesn't intervene somewhere
where it has economic interests. If it
goes and uh takes over Venezuela, it
actually gains something for its
economic interests, right? It it it
actually advances America's economic
interests. The Americans will not go and
bomb a country that works for them. The
US has a very large number of vasals
across the world. The Americans will
never bomb them or or or damage those
economies.
So it will intervene wherever there is
no damage to its economy. It will
intervene in where in various parts of
the world in such a way that it actually
enhances American power projection and
American control over the world. Right?
And why is the US so powerful? Because
it has almost global power projection
capabilities. It can intervene anywhere
on the surface of the planet at roughly
60 minutes notice. intervene militarily
because it has so many more than
probably 800 extra territorial military
bases spread across the world. That is
why right uh why does the US have these
advanced power possession capabilities?
Because
um some of the nations we talk about are
occupied physically occupied by the US
military like Japan, South Korea,
Germany, Italy etc. in terms in the case
of Europe. Well, Europe was beggared in
the aftermath of the Second World War.
The Americans helped rebuild their
economy and um and in exchange for that
Europe was vasalized and it was it was
acceptable to the Europeans because the
Americans were anyway the most powerful
military power in the world at the time.
The Europeans they were they were on
their knees after the second world war
and they just accepted whatever terms
they got. That's Europe. Then when it
comes to uh West Asia, the so-called
Middle East, well, once again, the
Americans have entered into various
kinds of arrangements with these nations
where the nations get the benefit of
American protection in exchange for
giving America their oil. So that's a
petro dollar system and so on. So power
is dependent at the bottom of the
hierarchy entirely on military power.
But it's also about creating economic
interdependence. It's also about
creating economic dependence more than
interdependence.
and uh it's about vasalizing countries
in a variety of ways and so on. It's
also about having the best technologies
and so on. So it's a multiplicity of
factors put together that uh give the US
these global essentially power
production capabilities. When it comes
to China and Russia, they have strong
militaries. Okay. Sure the Russia has a
strong military but Russia doesn't have
this network of anywhere in the world
apart from Belarus maybe. Yeah. Who
else? I suppose Belerus that's about it.
Have I missed somebody? Have I missed
something? Belerus. Does does Russia
have uh extr territorial military bases
naval in nature? No. It had Latakia. I'm
not sure what the situation with Latakia
is. What about China? Does China have
this sort of thing? A network of vasals.
It has North Korea. Iran is an all of
Vasal. So China has North Korea. That's
about it. And China doesn't have extra
territorial naval bases anywhere or
military bases across outside its
territory apart from maybe Jihodi or
maybe one or two things in Madagascar
which are like not really um you know
vasals vasal like relationships. So
China doesn't have anything like what
the US has and that's why the US is so
far ahead of everybody else.
Vidhi Manar says when India will become
the most powerful entity in the Indian
subcontinent Pakistan will become
irrelevant for us. But right now Russia
is the most powerful. Why? Then why does
Russia still have to deal with Ukraine?
Well, Russia still has to deal with
Ukraine because Russia is not the most
powerful entity
when it comes to Ukraine.
See, let's go to the map. It's it's a
great question actually. It's a great
question. Let's understand this in
relative terms.
So
here's the map. When it comes to the
Indian subcontinent, the Americans can
do a regime change in Pakistan. They can
occupy Afghanistan. They can do a regime
change in Nepal. They can do a regime
change in west in East Pakistan. They
can play around with Sri Lanka. They can
do all these things in India's backyard
and India has to simply watch and India
can't do a thing. India can't stop the
US from doing these things. That
indicates that in the Indian
subcontinent the US is the most powerful
geopolitical actor not India. So even in
the subcontinent the US is more powerful
than India. Okay that's that's just a
fact of life. So in the future someday
when India becomes more powerful than
than the US in its neighborhood that's
when Pakistan will naturally
disintegrate.
But that's someday in the future if it
whenever it happens. Now when it comes
to let's say Western Europe, you see the
most powerful geopolitical entity in
Western Europe isn't France, it isn't
Germany, it is the US. Okay? The US is
the most powerful
geopolitical and military entity in
Western Europe. when it comes to the
borderlands between Western and Eastern
Europe, between let's say Western Europe
and the Russian uh the Slavic regions,
that's where power overlaps.
So Ukraine was kind of neutral for a
while for a long time until 2014 when
the Americans uh did the Euroban coup in
Kiev and that's when Ukraine came under
American uh influence and you could say
control
and uh the the government the Americans
set up in in Ukraine it went ahead and
did all these atrocities against the
people of Donbas for like close to a
decade and so on and eventually this led
to the war. So why did the war happen?
because the American power in Ukraine
was becoming greater than Russian power
and this was a red line for Russia. If
Americans if Ukraine had become a member
of NATO let's say then you would had you
would have had American troops and nukes
on Russia's actual borders and that's
why Russia had to go to war. So this
tells you that the US is actually more
powerful in Ukraine than Russia because
even now even now Zalinski is in power
in Kiev and he is still getting
tremendous amounts of money and arms and
ammunition from the west from mainly the
European nations who are doing this at
the behest of the US. So it tells you
that in Ukraine the US is more powerful
than Russia you see. So in Ukraine,
Russia is less powerful than the US and
that's why the situation called the
Ukraine war exists. That is the truth.
Miganga Karbiswa says what's really
behind the old oil blockade on Cuba?
Another of Trump's Monro doctrine
impositions and Swami says what's going
on in Cuba? Why is the US blocking oil
shipments to Cuba and trying to strangle
its economy? Is an attack on Cuba
imminent? What do Americans gain by
attacking a small insignificant nation
like Cuba with no natural resources?
Let's take a look at the map and see
where Cuba is so that we can orient
ourselves and then we shall discuss what
is happening visav Cuba and the United
States. So Cuba so we go to the Atlantic
Ocean and Cuba is is this island over
here. Okay. It was uh I think Columbus
had at some point in time discovered
that this island. Um and Cuba it's it's
an island in the Caribbean Sea uh east
of the Gulf of Mexico.
And
so this is the island. It's not far from
Florida at all. If you see um the
distance you will see it's it's hardly
230 to 240 km from from the southern tip
of Florida and if we talk about key west
then it's even closer. So that that is
Cuba. Now Cuba has had this government
that has been independent and not
vasalized by the US for the longest
time. I mean you had the Cuban missile
crisis when Kennedy was president right
196 what 2 63 62
62 was the Cuban missile crisis. So Cuba
at the time was ruled by Fidel Castro.
It was aligned with the USSR
and uh the Soviets had imp placed
nuclear weapons and missiles in Cuban
territory and that's why the Cuban
missile crisis happened. So that goes
back to the 1960s 1962. It's in the
1950s I believe that Fidel Castro took
over the uh the island the control of
the island and became the dictator and
he died in the 21st century. His brother
Rahul Castro became president. I'm who's
the president of Cuba right now? Let's
quickly find out who's the president of
Cuba. Is it still Rahul Castro? Is he
alive? Who's the president
of Cuba?
Let's see. Miguel Dias Canel. Okay.
Whoever that is. So, so the deal is that
Cuba is
an actually independent nation
and it has uh opposed
US vasalhood for the longest time and it
has sided with the USSR in the past and
the Americans now are alleging that Cuba
is siding siding with Russia and China
and also Hezbollah and Hamas and
whatnot. So these are the allegations
the Americans are are are making on Cuba
and the Americans are saying that Cuba
is now a base from which anti-American
activities are being carried out.
So Cuba is harboring terrorists
apparently allegedly from Hezbollah
Hamas. is also uh handin glove with the
Russians and the Chinese to damage
American interests and that's why the
Americans say that they have imposed
this uh oil blockade on Cuba. So
obviously if you want to do a regime
change you need a justification for it
right even the Americans can't say that
you know we hate you and we want to just
get rid of you. They have to at least
you know keep up appearances to a
certain extent and and make some
allegations.
Um so the American Secretary of State
Marco Rubio
is a child of Cuban immigrants. So a
couple of years before Fidel Castro
became the president of Cuba or the
dictator of Cuba uh Rubio's parents
migrated to the US from Cuba and Rubio
and the cub and there's this big
Cubanamerican community in Florida. The
capital of Florida is Miami. It's a very
Cuban city, you know.
uh lots of Cuban origin people there and
these people who have escaped from Cuba
over the years and decades they are
strongly in favor of an American
mediated regime change operation in Cuba
so that Cuba becomes democratic again.
So there's a big uh big
constituency in Florida of Cubanameans
who support in favor a regime change in
Cuba and even Marco Rubio uh is in favor
of a regime change in Cuba. So that's
the political situation
and that's why the Americans have now
imposed this oil blockade on Cuba which
is devastating the Cuban economy. There
are power shortages and the hospitals
are have no power. It's a possibly a
humanitarian crisis and so on. The
objective is to demoralize the the Cuban
government, the Cuban people and to make
it impossible for the government to
continue u operating
and then when the time is right swoop in
and uh maybe do a regime change. Uh so
that is the objective of the United
States. Now why uh is the US doing this?
Why is the US doing this to a small
insignificant nation with no natural
resources? That's the question. It's
it's a good question. Cuba has no major
natural resources. Cuba imports oil from
it used to import oil from Mexico and
Venezuela. So Mexico, the Americans
aren't in Mexico and Mexico stopped
exporting oil to Cuba and then America
took over Venezuela. So even that
Venezuelan oil that was coming to Cuba
has stopped and now the Americans have
imposed a blockade, a naval blockade on
Cuba. So any oil tanker which is going
towards Cuba will be stopped and
impounded essentially. So no oil can
reach Cuba. So Cuba is now starving of
energy.
Why? Why? Why is Cuba significant?
Obviously, it has no natural resources.
So what is the deal? So first of all,
first of all, back to the map. Back to
the map. Back to the map. Cuba is it's
it occupies it's a big island and it's a
strategically important location, right?
Um obviously it's close to the US. The
Americans can do whatever they want in
this region. And uh the second thing is
obviously the the revived Trump Monro
doctrine. So Donald Trump has revived
the Mandro doctrine. The Monro doctrine
is this 1823 foreign policy of the
United States which stated that no
European or external power will be
allowed henceforth from 1823 onwards to
interfere in the internal affairs of any
nation in the Americas whether it is
North America, South America or Central
America.
Okay. So this foreign policy was adopted
by the Americans in 1823.
Trump has revived it. Trump says that
the US was now the US is now going to be
the super cop in the Americas. Whether
it's now South or Central America, no
external country is allowed to interfere
in the affairs of the Americas. Only the
US will decide what happens. And not
just that there is a Trump corollary on
this which says that any American nation
in the Americas if it goes against the
interests of the US in any way the
Americans will deal with it and take
care of it and you know yeah essentially
deal with it and that's what they've
done in Venezuela. So now they're
applying it to Cuba. Essentially what
the Americans want is that every single
nation in the Americas must be a proper
American basal. there will be no
disscent or opposition allowed anymore.
So what that tells us is that sooner or
later there's going to be a regime
change now in Cuba. Cuba has held out
for decades. How many decades? 60s 60s7s
80s 90s 2000s 2010s that's like 60 65
almost 70 years they've held out.
They've resisted. Looks like now time is
up for Cuba. Right. There we are. There
we are.
Right. Aush says, "US is now talking
about Venezuela as if it's an American
colony. The world will now purchase
Venezuelan oil resources, etc. They
boast like it's their own. Is being a
small nation a curse?"
Well, being a small Yeah. So, the
Americans now own Venezuela. They now
own and control Venezuelan oil, right?
Uh the Venezuelan government will be
allowed to sell oil, but on American
terms. So the Venezuel Venezuelan
government will be allowed to sell oil
either to American companies or to
nations that are approved by the US
and there is talk of Venezuelan
Venezuelan oil being sold to India with
the American stamp of approval. Right?
So the Americans now control the fate
and the economy of Venezuela. Terrible,
isn't it? Terrible. Terrible. Yes. Sad.
Sad and tragic. So, is being a small
nation a curse? Well, let me show you a
small nation.
Okay, let me show you a small nation and
let's decide if being a small nation is
a curse. We have this small nation here
called the UK. Yeah, the UK. It ruled
most of the world a century um a c 120
years ago. It ruled mo much of the
world. It ruled the whole of India. It
ruled much of Africa and much of the
world. The sun never set over the
British Empire. The UK is a small
nation, a small island nation. Is being
a small nation a curse? Being a small
nation is not necessarily curse. Just
like being a huge nation is not
necessarily a boon.
So what is the curse here? Weakness. The
greatest sin in geopolitics is weakness.
Okay? If you are weak, don't blame
others for your misfortunes. Why are you
weak? Why have you allowed yourself to
be in a situation where you have
weaknesses? It's weakness that puts you
in this situations. It's weakness that
allows others to take advantage of you.
The greatest sin in geopolitics is
weakness.
So
Venezuela,
its sin was weakness. If it had acquired
somehow, let's say, nuclear weapons or
something, then nobody would dare touch
it. Look at North Korea. Another small
nation. Does the US dare bully North
Korea? No, it doesn't. Right? So being a
small nation isn't a curse. It's not a
sin. Being a weak nation is a curse and
a sin. The greatest sin in geopolitics.
Remember that my friends.
Briankas says, "Now that the BNP,
Bangladeshi National Party has won and
Prime Minister Modi was quick to reach
out to Tariq Rahman. Do you think do you
feel India and Bangladesh can truly
reset relations after the strain under
Yunus or has too much trust already been
lost? Rushabd says the recent elections
in Bangladesh just concluded
BNP clean swept the elections with
two/3s plus majority. Jamaat too made
some gains. Tarik Rahman will most
likely be the new prime minister. Dr.
Deshunar had met him in Dhaka during
Khalida Zia's funeral. He is Kali Zia's
son and Prime Minister Modi too wished
him has there been something going on
between India and the BNP what do you
see ahead for Bangladesh for India for
Yunus and his aids and the US who has
takes here okay so there's been this
election in Bangladesh Bangladesh and
the BNP has won a massive majority right
two-thirds majority or something like
that and the head of the BNP is Tariq
Rahman he is the son of the late Khalida
the former prime minister of Bangladesh
and Khaled Azia was a two or three time
prime minister of Bangladesh and uh so
that that's the situation. So this guy
Tariq Kurman will most likely now going
to be is now most likely going to be the
new prime minister of Bangladesh and Dr.
Jashankar was there in Dhaka. He met
with this guy when you know during the
funeral of Khaled Azia the guy's mother
and the prime minister of India Mr. Modi
has sent out a tweet congratulating
Tariq Raman for his uh victory. So,
so what's going on? Here's something
going on between India and the BNP.
Listen, the Bangladeshi elections,
you know what kind of elections were
held in Bangladesh.
Imagine you had elections happening in
Nazi occupied France.
France was under Nazi occupation, right?
from whatever year to whatever year 1939
40 to whatever until the end of the
second world war or until the Normandy
invasion France was under Nazi
occupation the Vichi regime right so if
there was an election in France during
Nazi occupation would you call it a free
and fair election
would you call it a free and fair
election in which the major national
party is not allowed to stand is that a
free and fair election it's not it's
controlled by a foreign occupying force
the Nazis right similar to the election
you had in Bangladesh this
The Awami League was not allowed to
participate. It is a rigged election
from the very beginning. It's not a
democratic process
and it was held under Muhammad Yunus who
is an unelected dictator or puppet
dictator of Bangladesh.
Right? So the election was rigged from
the beginning and now BNP has won.
Now if the BNP has won it means they
have been allowed to win by the by the
by the power that controls Bangladesh.
Which power controls Bangladesh? The
United States. Ever since the coup
against Shadina happened, the US has
been in charge of Bangladesh. Right? The
Americans effected a regime change in
Bangladesh and they put Muhammad Yinus
in the position of chief adviser or
whatever the hell he is. Right? is just
a puppet, a figurehead
and the army is ruling Bangladesh.
So if Tariq Rahman has won and the BNP
has won, it's because they have been
allowed to win and most likely they will
continue to serve American interests.
So just because the prime minister has
wished this guy and just because
Jashungar, Dr. Jashungar met him in
Dhaka doesn't mean something is going on
between India and this guy or India and
the BNP. Okay, there is no master stroke
happening.
Maybe relations will be better between
India and Bangladesh. Maybe more
cordial, more polite relations, less
acrimony like we had the past ever since
the coup happened. I mean this fellow
Muhammad Inus has been putting out these
has been showcasing these books with uh
you know Bangladesh capturing you know
claiming Indian territory the far east
of India, the northeastern states of
India and so on. That's the kind of
provocations he's been doing. Maybe with
Kurman those provocations may cease and
the and the relationship becomes more
polite. But it doesn't mean that the
relationship improves.
Please understand the difference between
words and actions. Words can be words
don't matter.
Words don't matter. The actions is what
matters. So the question is what kind of
policies will Bangladesh now have
especially towards India going forward.
I very strongly suspect that nothing
much will change
now that Bangladesh now supposedly is
back on the democratic train which it
isn't actually but now we can claim
right the Americans always do this sham
elections somewhere or the other and
then they say okay everything is fine
and then they control things from behind
the scenes. I think that's what's going
to happen in Bangladesh. Okay. I don't
see any master stroke from India. Um you
know whatever he may be retired by the
Americans or whatever he may get a nice
plum position somewhere in some other
country. Maybe he'll move to New York
City or something or maybe he'll stay in
Bangladesh as a highly respected noble
laurate or whatever. It doesn't matter.
Yunus is not important. Yunus is not a
powerful person. He is not in power.
He's simply the the face, the
figurehead, the puppet. He's not a
person of any importance. Okay? So it
doesn't matter what happens to Muhammad
Inus, he is anyway not in power. Now
there's going to be this Tariq Rahman
guy who's going to be in power. It's
kind of like Shabbash Shar being in
power. That's kind of what what it's
going to be like. So India the Indian
government may say that you know what we
will better relations and that sort of
thing. But at the end of the day the
real question is what kind of policies
will Bangladesh adopt? Will they change
from the policies we've had in the past
year and a half?
Will Bangladesh continue to claim Indian
territory? Will Bangladesh continue its
persecution of Hindus, its massacres of
Hindus? Will Bangladesh continue
whatever it is doing in the far east of
India?
Will Bangladesh
continue its relationship with Pakistan
with the ISI? These are the questions
you should be asking.
I think these things will continue.
These nice tweets and handshakes and
all, they don't they are of no
importance whatsoever. So let's wait and
watch how this evolves. This guy Tarik
Raman becomes the new prime minister
most likely. What kind of policies will
he adopt. Let's see the next 6 months. I
suspect nothing much will change. Maybe
the behavior will become more polite.
The relationship will become more
cordial but behind the scenes the same
policies will continue. Then what's the
big deal? What's the big difference?
Nothing. Nothing has changed then. So
that's what I think will continue.
Rushab Tar says, "Your views on the
recent elections election in Japan. The
LDP alone secured a two-thirds majority
in a plurality in their upper house. So
they can constitutionally do anything
they want if they want." My question is
will will madame Sai Takichi amend
article 9 and pursue a peaceful as well
as pursue a peaceful as well as nuclear
weapon program which is an agenda given
that her party has a super majority or
will she face issues like Abisan and how
does this impact China and India?
Okay. So, Abasan
wanted Japan to actually amend its
constitution and move away from the
American imposed pacifism and so on. And
uh we know what happened to Abisan sadly
tragically.
Uh now Madame Saii has won a massive
massive majority, super majority,
two-thirds majority. Um, and this gives
her the power to amend the Japanese
constitution. The Japanese constitution
has been in force since 1945.
Who wrote the Japanese constitution? The
American occupiers of Japan wrote the
Japanese constitution. It was not
written by the Japanese people. This
constitution was written by the
Americans. It was imposed upon the
Japanese people in the nation of Japan.
And since 1945 all the way until today,
not one word has changed. The Japanese
people have not been allowed to change a
single word of the constitution. Now,
Madame Saiichi
potentially has the power to do that if
she wants.
The question is, will she amend change
the constitution? What is article 9?
Right? That's that's the big question
here. It's the pacifist article. Okay.
Article 9 of Japan Constitution, the
pacifism clause, the landmark no war
clause that legally renounces war as a
sovereign right, prohibits the threat of
force or use of force to settle
international disputes and pledges not
to maintain land, sea or air forces.
And despite this, Japan maintains the
civil defense forces for defensive
purposes. Key provisions clause one,
renunciation of war. Japan permanently
renounces war as a sovereign right which
means Japan is no longer a sovereign
nation right and the threat or use of
force as a means of settling
international disputes. Second clause no
war potential land sea and air forces as
as as well as the other air potential
war potential will never be maintained.
Right of belligerency
the right of belligerency of the state
is not recognized so and so on. So the
Japanese government interprets the
constitution to allow the maintenance of
the SDF for the minimum necessary
self-defense which obviously you know
works for the Americans because it
allows the Americans to counter China.
Yeah. Uh that sort of thing. So that's
the article 9. That's article 9 of the
Japanese constitution. Now Sonai could
potentially have it changed. Even if he
can potentially do it, will she actually
do it?
Will she amend article 9 and say that
Japan now has the right to fight war to
wage war? I
in my opinion she will do it if the
Americans allow it.
Does it make sense for America to turn
Japan into a different kind of country
now? A country that can actually
initiate warfare again for the first
time since the 1940s.
Does it make sense for the Americans to
allow Japan to do that?
And does it make sense for the US to
allow Japan to have nuclear weapons?
Maybe it does.
Maybe it's time to to uh counter China
more vigorously, more rubously. So if
the if the Americans are concerned about
China and China's potential to take
Taiwan or potential to do whatever
mischief in the region, then the
Americans could allow Sai Takahi to to
do these things. The point is if Sai
Taki decides to do something
unilaterally, she will face problems.
She will face issues. But if she does
this with the approval of the US behind
the scenes, then it will go smoothly.
It's I think likely that the the that
the nation of Japan will have nuclear
weapons by 2027 28. Most like I think
it's likely and I've spoken about this
on multiple occasions. I say this
because one of the reasons I say this is
because uh Henry Kissinger the great man
had predicted the year he died 2023 that
Japan will most likely have nuclear
weapons in 5 years and the guy knew what
he was talking about. So um that's one
indicator that this could happen.
So I think Sayata may be empowered by
the Americans if they think it makes
sense for Japan to become a more robust
and more vigorous and more proactive
counterforce counterbalance to China. In
that case they will allow it. What does
it mean for China and India? Obviously
it is bad for China. The Japanese SDF
self-defense forces are very capable.
Very capable. The Japanese submarines
are scary. The Chinese are scared of
Japanese submarines. The Japanese Soryu
class submarines are some of the best in
the world. The Soryu class submarines
that the Japanese Navy has
decommissioned
are better than the existing Indian Navy
submarines. The decommissioned
submarines are better than India India's
active submarines. That's and and
imagine how good the active succass
submarines will be. Right? So uh the
Japanese navy the Japanese submarines
overall tremendously powerful. the China
is is really really concerned about
Japan Japan's uh military capabilities
the way things stand as of today. So if
Japan goes ahead and amends the article
know maybe removes the article line of
constitution and goes nuclear that's
going to be tremendously concerning for
China for India good for India actually
if that happens good for India
real says do you think China has an
upper hand in this cold war because of
their industrial complex and education
system educational standards have
declined significantly in the US so far
better than India I suppose when you say
vishuru I suppose you're saying India
and China probably has the best
education system in the world. What are
my what are my my thoughts? Okay. Um do
I think China has an upper hand in the
cold war because their industrial
complex because of their manufacturing
over capacity their high techch um you
know manufacturing capabilities and
their education system. Clearly these
things these these factors these are
massive factors when it comes to um
where where a nation stands in any kinds
any kind of u geopolitical race. So like
I explained earlier there are multiple
factors that go into these things. You
you need to have resources right? China
has lots of resources but it lacks some
resources um like oil and gas that it
lacks. It also lacks various critical
minerals and so on which it acquires
from Africa and other countries. Uh
China has the best manufacturing uh uh
industrial capacity in the world. The
best manufacturing in the world in China
is neck to neck with the US in terms of
various technologies. The Chinese have
really really invested in human capital
in uh their education system uh the the
technology which which allows them to
develop high-tech products the knowledge
they have. So unless you develop you
invest significantly in education in
science, technology, engineering
education, medicine education, you won't
be able to become a major industrial
power. So the Chinese probably like you
say I agree with you probably have the
best education system in the world now.
They have invested trillions of dollars
into their education system since the
1980s and 1990s and it has genuinely
genuinely bore fruit for the Chinese. So
the Chinese well one must salute them
one must commend them for what they've
achieved. They've put in the work
they've put in the money and they've
over the years step by step improved
their education system to to a place
where today it is world class probably
the best in the world. So because of
this tremendous
human capital quality that the Chinese
have, the best education system,
tremendous human human capital,
tremendous manufacturing capabilities,
which obviously transforms or translates
into um military manufacturing also,
right? The Chinese are able to now
manufacture jet engines and uh fifth and
sixth generation fighter planes. They're
improving the submarines. So obviously
this this goes into military u the
military sphere as well. So in these
matters in some of these matters the
Chinese have the upper hand of the US.
When it comes to AI they're neto neck in
the US. Uh when it comes to certain
technologies they are slightly behind
but not very far behind right. Uh so
that's the situation
right so yeah they are ahead in all the
they are ahead or neck to neck with the
US in these things. So does this mean
that the Chinese have an upper hand in
the cold war? Well, not quite. The
Chinese don't have any power production
capabilities. They have no missiles.
That's where the US is far ahead of
China. The US is also far ahead of China
in in terms of the space race. Way ahead
of China. The Americans can deploy
hundreds thousands of miss of of of
satellites, right? The American
government is about possibly about
10,000 satellites in orbit of various
kinds. A lot of these are military
satellites and spy satellites, right?
And the Americans have like 40,000 or so
starling satellites which may also
double up as as surveillance equipment
possibly. Right? So that's where the
Americans have an unmatched advantage.
The Chinese are doing their best to
replicate you know uh controlled landing
technologies and reusable rocket
technologies and they are doing good in
this. India is not even part
participating in the race. The Chinese
are trying to catch up with the US but
they are still behind in these matters.
But when it comes to power projection,
the Americans have an unmatched
capability. The Chinese can't even dream
of the kind of power projection the
Americans have and the kind of the
number of vas the Americans have. In
terms of nuclear capabilities, the
Chinese are far behind. I I suspect
possibly. But they once again they're
trying their best to narrow the gap. So
because of these factors, the Americans
significantly have have a significant
upper hand in this cold war. Right? And
the main issue is that the Chinese are
not self-sufficient in terms of energy
and the Americans can control the energy
flows around the world and that is one
of the Achilles heels of China. The
China can weaponize its control over the
rare earth's exports and you know rare
earth magnets and so on. So it has
leverage over the US which it has built
up yeah overall over the years through
hard work unlike India. So the Chinese
have some leverage over the US, but the
US has way more leverage over China. And
overall, the US is still significantly
ahead of China in this cold war. But AI
could be the the game changer. We'll see
about that.
Brown Leprechaun says the US couldn't
even defeat the Houthis in 7 months. Why
do they think they will be able to
defeat Iran?
Okay, let's go to the map and understand
what we are discussing here. where is
map is here. So here's the map and we're
talking about Yemen.
So
the Houthis are the Ansarah faction in
Yemen
and um they oppose the US. They are
aligned with Iran.
They used to be aligned with Syria but
Syria has fallen now and they are also
aligned with you could say Lebanon and
Hbah.
So Syria has fallen.
Bashar al-Assad no longer rules Syria.
There's an ISIS terrorist who rules
Syria now. Um Julani is an American
vasal. Uh so that's the situation. Now
the the Houthis one going back to the
map uh they oppose the US and they have
uh reasonably high quality missiles and
using that they have from time to time
blockaded the straight of Bab al- Mandib
this narrow geographical choke point
that connects uh the Red Sea with the
Gulf of Adan that opens up into the
Indian Ocean the western Indian Ocean
the so-called Arabian Sea so the Houthis
have been able to blockade the strait of
Babal Mandib from time to time. And
since 2024, the Americans have uh
uh they have launched hundreds of air
strikes at the Houthis
and uh and still the Houthis exist. They
haven't been a regime changed out of
existence, right? The Houthis are still
in control of northern Yemen. At least
the Americans haven't been able to uh
dislodge them from power and place some
somebody else in power, right? Uh the
Americans u have also used uh local
allies in this uh um this conflict
against the Houthis most notably Saudi
Arabia and the UAE. in the Saudi sa in
the in in the UAE were in this coalition
uh which uh
was fighting against the Houthis
the past 10 10 or so years right uh and
still the Houthis are still in power in
northern Yemen uh the Americans have
launched hundreds of air strikes on them
um and they have been able to partially
end the blockade of the uh straight of
Babal Mand maybe fully also at times but
they haven't been able to regentage the
Houthis. Now, here's the thing. The
Americans never actually seriously tried
to uh end the rule of the Houthis.
They never actually launched a land
invasion. It was just air strikes
and uh drone strikes and so on to ensure
that the the straight is open. That's
it. The Americans have never gone in
militarily the way they went into Iraq
or something, right? 2023 Iraq, the
American invasion of Iraq, the they or
the uh 2003, sorry, 2003 invasion of
Iraq or the invasion of Afghanistan, the
Americans did
this sort of thing. The Americans have
never attempted in Yemen. So, they
haven't really tried to do a regime
change in Yemen. they've used their
allies like Saudi Arabia and the UAE
to to offset the the Houthis in Yemen.
Uh and of late there have been you know
there have been uh frictions between the
Saudis and the and the UAE as well
because of differing because of
diverging geopolitical objectives which
is a different story entirely. So the US
hasn't really seriously tried to defeat
the Houthis
since 2024. They haven't really
seriously tried it. they have simply
tried to suppress their capabilities so
that you know the strait remains open.
So that's the deal. Will the so does
this indicate the Americans won't be
able to defeat Iran? It doesn't indicate
that. Defeating Iran will be a
monumental task. It will be very
difficult and it will be very costly,
very expensive, very timeconuming and it
it may even lead to setbacks,
at least temporary setbacks. But the
Americans do have the firepower to
defeat Iran if they decide to go allin.
It will be much more difficult than the
American invasion of Saddam Hussein's
Iraq. It will be much more difficult and
uh much more expensive, much more
timeconuming. But the Americans can do
it. If they are serious about it, they
can.
This is Hersh Kapoor says, "In an era
where economies, militaries, and
civilian life are deeply dependent on
space-based infrastructure, does the
weaponization of satellites represent a
more immediate and systemic threat to
global stability than nuclear weapons?
And should international law evolve to
treat large-scale satellite attacks as
acts equivalent to strategic nuclear
aggression?
Okay. So, ASAT warfare you're talking
about, right? And the weaponization of
satellites
So when it comes to the modern
economies, the world economy, it's all
interconnected, right? When it comes to
military matters, when it comes to
civilian life, all of these
domains,
all of these are deeply integrated with
satellites for a variety of things,
right? Communications, we are
communicating right now. Much of that
depending on where you are will be
happening through satellite. We depend
on satellites for communications, for
navigation, for timing, for militaries
depend on satellites for intelligence,
for missile warning, for early missile
warning systems. We depend on satellites
for finance, for logistics and so many
things.
So if satellites are are are weaponized
or satellites are disrupted, you know,
then let's say a small number relatively
small number of key satellite systems
are disrupted in some ways. So this
could paralyze banking systems. This
could paralyze uh air traffic management
systems. It could uh paralyze large
parts of the internet. It could also
paralyze the command and control
structures of various military
militaries. Right? So space systems,
satellite systems, satellite
infrastructure. These are critical
infrastructure. Now these are now
treated as critical infrastructure and
these are fragile systems. Right? So
that is the situation. Now what do we
mean by weaponized satellites? You're
asking about weaponized satellites.
Yeah. So,
how do you weaponize satellites or how
do you bring satellites into the domain
of warfare? So, one way of doing that
military means is uh ASAT weapons,
anti-satellite weapons, you know, ground
launched missiles or air launched
missiles which will intercept a
satellite in orbit and destroy it. So,
that's a kinetic ASAT weapon, you know,
anti-atellite weapon. So these weapons
physically destroy satellites and they
create a profusion of debris which is a
disaster. Then you also have non-kinetic
tools non-kinetic means of disrupting
satellites like jamming like spoofing um
dazzling or blinding of sensors cyber
attacks against against satellites or or
cyber attacks against the ground station
that controls the satellite or or
interfaces with the satellite. this this
this sort of thing. These are
non-kinetic tools, right? Um and you
also have concepts of nuclear armed
satellites. I mean, if you watch James
Bond movies from the 1980s and 1990s, in
the 20th century, there are concepts of
nuclear armed satellites. Uh and we've
had space-based nuclear detonations. The
Americans and the Russians both have u
you know tested nuclear weapons in
orbits in in orbit in Earth orbit. So if
you have a nuclear detonation in orbit
today and if you well depending on where
the detonation happens it can disable
entire constellations of satellites
right so clearly um space is now on the
verge of being uh weaponized we
certainly have the means and the tools
for doing that uh so overall
the weaponization of satellites is
you could say it's a risk multiplier
it's a systemic risk multiplier. It is a
systemic risk multiplier for nuclear
danger. It's not a separate threat. It's
not a higher order threat. It's a risk
multiplier for nuclear danger. So, if
there's an attack on satellite
infrastructure, this will obviously
disrupt like I said global finance,
navigation, communications.
It will uh create uh systemic shocks,
you know, economic shocks, political
shocks. And this will happen without
ever crossing the nuclear threshold.
Yeah.
uh it will make it harder for militaries
to monitor what their adversaries are
doing. If there are agreements between
two nations, maybe arms control
agreements. If satellites are taken out
of service, out of commission, then
you'll not be able to monitor and
enforce armed arms control agreements or
whatever. So if this happens, if if
satellites are taken out, if if space is
weaponized, this will increase opacity
during time of crisis, the fog of war,
like they say, you know, friction and
this will have the effect of raising the
possibility, the probability that
nuclear weapons could be used either in
confusion or in panic. So nuclear
weapons are still way more dangerous
than satellites and the satellite the
weaponization of satellites and
weaponization of space.
So uh so
so the weaponization of satellites is
still you know not the most dangerous
thing in the world. It's it's a it's a
risk multiplier. Nuclear weapons remain
the most decisive existential danger for
human beings. It it they remain the most
decisive existential danger for the
planet. Um satellites are a separate
thing. They are connected but they are
different. And today you if you have
nuclear weapons deployed in space you
know or nuclear operations in space that
kind of blurs the line between a space
war and a nuclear war. And uh so that's
where we are. So I would not say that
international law needs to international
law can evolve to you know probably you
can't really treat large scale satellite
attacks as something that's equivalent
to strategic nuclear aggression. But the
lines are blurring now because it's all
all interconnected. So it's a it's a
strategic risk multiplier. It's a
systemic risk multiplier.
Dodasputra says at one point last year
you had said that tribalism and
civilization are opposites. Okay. I have
thought a lot about that statement. You
have said that rise in tribalism is a is
a sign of decay of civilization. Yeah.
Isn't it?
Oh, okay. I don't know if you have
followed Balaji's work but Balaji has
showed with examples how the US is
becoming more tribal in terms of red
tribe versus blue tribe how they don't
marry into each other they don't go to
each other's schools they don't want to
live in the same city so you have blue
cities and red cities right now
combining these thoughts is it fair to
say that civilization in the US is in
particular is in decay and some of the
geopolitical churns we are witnessing
could be because of that I know that
still have phenomenal amount of hard
power.
So yes, I I I must have said this. I
don't remember but I must have said it
that uh tribalism is the enemy and the
opposite of of civilization. Tribalism.
What is tribalism? It it means that
within a civilization you have these
special interest groups that emerge who
have shared interests that are opposite
to the interest of a different group.
Think about India. Do we have categories
of people in India who are who are
pitted against each other?
Some get some people get more rights and
some people are are some people are
portrayed as permanent oppressors and
some people are permanent victims.
Right? So,
so some groups have shared interests and
other groups have shared interests and
these interests are opposing forces.
Right? So, this is called tribalism.
This is called tribalism. In India,
reservation is creating tribalism, isn't
it? So tribal so that is going to
destroy the civilization if it
continues. So tribalism is the enemy of
civilization. Tribalism eventually
causes the collapse of civilization. I
don't know what the government of India
is doing. Is the government of India
intending to destroy India civilization?
That's the question, right? Anyhow, so
that's the deal with tribalism. Now um
I'm not sure about what Balaji has said
but uh the US is indeed becoming more
tribal red versus blue right yeah they
don't marry among each other they don't
go to each other's schools they don't
live in the same city and and so on
so yeah there is increasing tribalism in
the US um the US society you could say
is kind of declining because of all
these things now so therefore should is
it correct to say that civilization
is declining and decaying in the US.
Well,
I have never seen the US as a
civilization.
Was Rome a civilization? Rome was not a
civilization. Rome was an empire.
It was the most powerful entity in
west of Suez
more or less, wasn't it? For the long
for like a couple of centuries or two
and a half centuries or so. So Rome was
not a civilization. It absorbed elements
of various civilizations including
Greece, Greek civilization, Egyptian
civilization and so on. Maybe even
Celtic elements, but overall it was an
empire. It was not a civilization. The
United States is very much like a
modernday Rome. It's not a civilization.
It's an empire. So I have never seen the
US as a civilization. They like to talk
about Western civilization, whatever
that is. I don't know what western
civilization is.
West, the west itself in the past 500
years has been an imperialistic force,
an imperialistic set of entities.
Whether it's the Portuguese or the
Spanish or the French or the English and
now the Americans, these are
imperialistic
entities and these are empires, empires
that rose and fell. So the US is an
imperial entity. It's not a
civilization.
Um and overall society in the US is in
indeed decaying and declining. Right?
there's more tribalism. There is all
there are all these divisions in the US
being exhausted exacerbated by
politicians and so on. So yes, we are
indeed seeing the slow gradual decline
and decay of American society.
I agree with that. They still have a
phenomenal amount of hard power. You are
absolutely right. I agree with you. Uh
but I don't see the US as a
civilizational entity. I see it as an
imperial entity and that's where I
differ.
Reneigan says in one of your interviews
by Adi Achinit you mentioned that the
Shans were are mostly Baptists today but
they are the ones who brought Vishnu
idol to Manipur in the 15th century. The
place where the temple is built is
called Vishnapur. Bishanpur. Vishnu
Bishanpur it used to be called now it's
Vishnapur. Okay. And thus came Vishnu
Priya. Well the Vishnu Priyas are not
really
are they really mates? Are they really
Manipuris? They claim they are the
original ones but I not sure about that
at all. Anyhow, uh Bishnob, right? The
Shans were known as Pongs by the Maic
Kings. In the twilight of Burma as this
movie, right? The Australian Austrian
lady who married the Shan king was named
Mahadevi.
Why didn't India capitalize on its roots
in the Shan state? Manipur shared
borders with Thailand. Yeah, correct.
So, going back to the map, where's the
map? Here's the map.
Uh Shan state, right? Northern Myanm
northern Burma.
So we're talking about northern Burma
here, Shan state and that used to be
obviously a Vishnavite region and the
kingdom of Manipur was much much larger
in the past whereas uh
yeah the king of Manipur had captured
Manderlay as well at one point in time.
Long story uh yeah so it was a much much
larger entity Manipur and uh Shan state
was a neighboring uh kingdom.
And today the people in the earth who
live in the earthwan state are mostly
Baptist Christians who have been
converted to Christianity by American
missionaries in the past century or so
similar to what happened in India's far
east again done by American missionaries
with the help of Mr. Neruji um in the
past 100 years or so. Um so now coming
back to your uh question.
Um
so the kingdom of Manipur in the in the
Shan kingdom had good relations and uh
the Shan king brought a Vishnu statue
Morty to Manipur in the 15th century and
eventually Manipur adopted the path of
Vishnuism. The kings did that and
eventually the whole of Manipur became
Vishnabite
synretatized with the original
polytheistic culture sanism which is
calledism in English. Uh so we had this
right
Shan state was was Hindu today it's
Baptist.
So the question at the end you asking is
a pertinent question. Why didn't India
capitalize on its roots in Shan state?
Civilizational and cultural roots in
Shan state. Manipur shared a border with
Thailand. See if you look at the
geography. Okay, let's go back to the
map.
Shan state was Hindu.
Myanmar was Hindu and Buddhist
originally Hindu. Thailand
was Hindu. Thailand still has lots of
Hindu elements. Their kings are still
called King Rama of the Chakri dynasty,
right? Uh Singapore, Singapore Hindu.
Malaysia was used to be Hindu. Indonesia
was all Hindu. The Philippines were
Hindu. Vietnam, Cambodia, Laos, all were
Hindu. You had Hinduism all the way to
the Philippines. Tibet was Buddhist.
Gandhar was Hindu. We had Indian roots
all over the place.
Right? So the question is why didn't
India capitalize on its civilizational
and cultural roots in Shan state? Well,
I can give you the example of Tibet.
Tibet when India became independent in
1947 was an independent entity.
It should have been India's
protectorate. Tibet was part of the
Indosphere. But what did we do? We
handed Tibet on a plate to China. When
the Chinese troops started starving
because it was so far from China, the
government of India sent thousands of
tons of rice to the Chinese soldiers.
That's how we dug our own grave and
ended our civilizational existence in
Tibet.
After 1947,
the governments of India have been
hindophobic governments, secular
governments.
Any anything that has anything to do
with money with with Hinduism is
anathema. Hinduism evil, Hinduism bad,
Hinduism backward, Hinduism regressive.
Let's not do have anything to do with
Hinduism. That's been the policy of
every successive government of India
after 1947.
Right?
So that's why India did not capitalize
on its cultural and civilizational roots
in Shan state. I mean nations like like
Burma, like Thailand would have been
very happy to have had India as the
protector, the military protector of the
region. But India did not want to play
the role
and that's why the US had to step in. We
just opened up the space if we seeded
the space to the US. Right?
In 1947, India had the most powerful
navy in Asia. Do you know that? What on
earth did the governments of India do
after after 47? I really wonder.
So India simply abandoned its children.
India switched off its civilizational
status. India reduced itself to a nation
state.
Forget about Shan state. Forget about
Thailand. How did India treat the states
in the far east, the far eastern
regions, Manipur, Nagal and etc.
Stepmotherly treatment. Neu opened up
the whole place for Christian
missionaries, Baptist missionaries and
shut the door for every for all Hindu
and you know Indic religions.
The the the consequence of this is that
in a few decades the whole region was
civilization was civilizationally
destroyed culturally destroyed.
The beautiful indigenous culture of
Nagaland destroyed much of Manipur
destroyed Arunachal it's happening now
it's still happening it's not like it's
it's from the days of NU it's still
happening by the way still happening
so India failed to capitalize on its
civilizational roots even in in India
so this all boils down to a lack of
leadership or the or lack of quality
leadership
It's tragic what India has done to
itself and still continues doing
real Putin says what's the possibility
of Dwal taking over India the way Putin
took over Russia
okay
what is Dwaler's age today must be 80 81
82 let's find out
okay must be in the early 80s maybe 82
Uh Jit Dal age what's his age? 81 years
old. Okay. Uh Vlah Vadimir
Putin age in 1999. How old was he? 47.
Vladimir Putin was a young man. In
political terms he was a young man. 47
is young for a politician. He was a
young man when he took over the
the reigns of Russia in 1999 47. Ajit
Dual sir is 81 years old today. 81.
When do you expect he may have the
chance to take over? He may be 83 84 85
at the time. Do you want a leader of
India who's 85 years old? Mr. Ajit Dual
is a great man. He has had a legendary
career,
an incredible career. Someday the truth
of of all his great actions will come
out. Maybe in a few decades when it is
declassified. That's how great he is.
But he is in his 80s now.
Do we want leaders who are in their 80s?
Isn't it better to have leaders who are
much younger?
Right? Maybe in their 40s or 50s. Maybe
40s is a little too young perhaps for
politics. uh maybe 50s.
So I think that may not be a very viable
possibility. I'm not sure if Mr. Dwal
even wants to take over in that sense.
You know, I don't think that is his
calling in life. I he would know better
than me obviously. I'm just guessing
here. But I think it is unlikely. You
see,
then again, he's not a politician,
right? He's not a politician. Do you see
Mr. Dwal sitting standing for election
and all that campaigning? No man,
I'm not sure that is the the the
path he would like to take.
Amisha Mishra says is the younger Das
theory a real thing? So what is this
younger Das theory? First of all there
is a set of events that actually
happened and then there's a theory. So
what is the set of events that actually
happened? So about 12,900
years before today, there's a sudden
onset of cold weather all across the
planet. Sudden ice age.
Okay. See, let's find out the last
glacial minimum.
Last glacial minimum. Last glacial
maximum. Maximum.
The last glacial maximum
was about 29 to 19,000 years ago. The
coldest most intense phase of the last
ice age featuring maximal global icy ice
sheet expansion.
Glaciers covered about 8% of Earth's
surface, 25% of land and so on. The sea
levels dropped by 120 m compared to what
we have today. The world was
significantly colder and so on and so
forth. The last glacial maximum was
between 29,000 to 19,000 years ago. uh
average temperature
what was the average temperature in the
planet
uh 8° Celsius was the average global
temperature okay so that is the last
glacial maximum now what about the
younger
younger driest period that's about
that's about 12,900 years ago per period
okay 12,9 900 to 11,700 years ago about
a,000 or 1,300 years it lasted. Okay. Uh
average temperature.
So the average temperature at that time,
what was the average temperature? Okay,
it's showing you how much it fell. So in
Greenland, the temperature fell by about
10°C. Imagine a drop of 10°C. And the
northern hemisphere temperatures dropped
by about 3 to 3 to 5° C. So this younger
das period was a period of about 1,000
years 1300 years beginning 12,900 years
before today where the global
temperatures abruptly dropped abruptly
sudden drop across the world. Uh maybe
in the northern hemisphere where we live
most of us it was 3 to 5° C kind of drop
in Greenland it was about 10 to 10 to 13
or 15° uh of of drop in temperature.
That's massive massive drop of
temperature and this la this happened
abruptly. It lasted for about 1,000 or
1300 years and then it disappeared
abruptly. So for these
temperatures fell in a period of of
about 50 to 70 to 100 years in just
about one century the temperatures
dropped that much. Then this period
lasted for about 1,000 or 1300 years and
then about in about 30 to 50 years the
temperatures went back to normal.
So that is the younger das period.
Now the question so it's it actually did
happen. The question is how did it
happen? What was the causitative factor
or set of causitive factors? That is the
question and that's where the
controversy arises.
So I'm not sure what the officially
accepted consensus is as to the
causitive factors for the youngest
younger dria's cooling of the earth. But
there's another theory. The theory is
that there was an impact event, maybe an
asteroid or a comet that hit the earth
or maybe broke into pieces and hit
multiple parts of the earth and multiple
air bursts and all that and maybe a lot
of dust and soot was pushed up into the
atmosphere which cooled the planet for
about a thousand or so years. That
that's that's a theory. That's the
younger das impact theory
and it's been put forth by people like
Graham Hancock.
Younger dra impact theory. The question
is what evidence do we have that such an
impact happened? Maybe a cometary impact
or an asteroid impact. Did we have
single impact? Do we have multiple
impacts? Sometimes comets and asteroids
break up and they hit you in multiple
places. That sort of thing also happens.
Um so do we have any evidence of an
impact event? There's this Greenland
impact crater that's been discovered
recently. So uh green land uh crater
younger.
Yeah. So it kind of dates to that time.
31 km wide. Hiata crater.
Initially suspected blah blah blah. It's
okay. It happened 58 million years ago.
Oh well that's tragic. It's 58 million
million years older than the younger
dest thing. Okay. So, I remember seeing
this news that there that there's this
crater that's been discovered in
Greenland that kind of could prove the
younger dus impact theory, but now I I
didn't look it up until now. So, it's 58
million years old. Well, that's that's
sad. So, I'm not sure if there's any
evidence that that corroborates this
theory, the younger dry impact event
theory. So uh most scientists and
researchers do not treat this theory
very seriously primarily because of a
lack of evidence that supports it.
But it's still um it's still
theoretically possible. So maybe the
impact creators are hiding somewhere.
Maybe they haven't discovered them or
something. That's also a possibility.
But in the absence of so the absence of
evidence is not evidence of absence. But
we need to have evidence before we take
a theory. seriously and we don't have it
right now. Uh and there are some other
pieces of evidence very circumstantial
evidence. There is gope a swarm of
planets kind of thing. Okay. Goe
uh the carvings there. Uh come swarm.
Let's see. Ancient carvings carvings on
pillar 43 are impacted are interpreted
as a record of a devastating comet swarm
impact about 10,850 BC younger dest
thing. Okay, let's see a pillar 43 and
go.
What's it look like? So, do we see a
swarm of comets?
I can see a scorpion. Do I see a swarm
of comets?
I'm not sure if I see a swarm of comets,
but I don't know, maybe some people see
that. So, it's it's a very
circumstantial, far-fetched kind of
thing, but some people interpret that
pillar as the as some kind of record of
a
swarm of comets appearing and impacting
the earth and setting of the younger dra
period. But clearly, that's just very
very circumstantial and very
far-fetched. Can't be taken as proof.
Okay.
Nirmana Shanks says, "What specific
economic and political reforms did Den
Shaoping introduce to start the rise of
modern China?" A relevant question. Very
relevant question, important question.
What policies did Ding Shopping create?
Which did he abolish or modify? And how
did these changes transform the Chinese
economy and society? What major
challenges did he face from within the
party, the bureaucracy and society at
large? And how did he overcome them to
establish the path that led to China's
global emergence? Thank you for your
attention to the matter. So the amount
of questions you've packed into this one
comment to answer them satisfactorily
and properly it would take me probably
like a several hours to go into all of
this in detail. So how about I give you
like the top three you know policies of
Ding Shopping that that that contributed
to China's China's rise the rise of
modern China. So Ding Shopping comes to
power what 1978 when did he come to
power? late '7s probably 78 79
Ping when did he
uh when when did he come to power
power then shopping 1977
okay and he became the paramount leader
of China in December 1978 okay so that's
when Ding Shaoping uh became the
paramount leader of China 1978.
So the first thing he did see before
1978, China was a proper communist
nation. It was a collectivi
collectivized economy. Everything was
collectivist in nature. Farming was a
collective enterprise. Right? So
after Ding Shawing came to power, he
dismantled
collective farming. Okay?
See in collective farming everything was
owned by the state. Individuals owned
nothing. Families own nothing. They did
not own the land. They did not own their
own household, their own house. They did
not own the produce of the farmland.
They own nothing. The state owned
everything. They the the farmers the
peasants were simply well essentially
peasants of slaves who were owned by the
Chinese Communist Party. So from the
time Deng shaing came to power, he
almost immediately dismantled collective
farming. He uh gave limited land use
rights to individual farmers and their
families, right? And they were mandated
to deliver a certain kota of of
agricultural produce to the state and
they were allowed to keep the surplus or
even sell the surplus.
So that's a transformative
reform in China. Okay. So before that
everything they produced was had to be
given to the state and then they would
be given a certain amount of
whatever produce to stay alive you know
to to survive and that's why we had
these horrific things like the the the
famines that Mao engineered in his great
leap forward in the green revolution and
whatn not. So then shopping
gave farmers the right to to uh keep the
surplus after they delivered the kota to
the state and um
and the Chinese and then shopping made
rural markets legal again. So farmers
could set up markets and sell the
produce to to whoever wanted to buy it,
you know. So and and they could keep the
profits, they could keep the money, that
sort of thing. So because of this uh
this incentivized farmers to grow more
and to produce more. So grain output
shot up. The income of farmers that also
shot up. It rose significantly by the
early 1980s. The chronic food shortages
that plagued China and and caused the
horror famines of of the Maadong era.
Those chronic shortages of food, those
ended. And over time this this had the
effect of creating a large rural
purchasing power capability. You know
they they could start purchasing things.
They could start they could become
consumers over time. So uh and because
of this farmers were also allowed to
diversify into cash crops and activities
that were non-farming activities. So
this eventually gave rise to uh various
kinds of small cottage industries and
enterprises. Eventually the whole
countryside became gradually
industrialized. It absorbed the surplus
labor. So this was the first major
reform that I can think of from Ding
Shopping. Uh the second big reform was
the open door policy that Ding Shopping
you know implemented.
So 1969 China and the USSR almost go to
war. The USSR decides to nuke China. The
Americans save China. The US then has
this they taunt with the Chinese. You
know, Nixon and Kissinger come to
Beijing and meet Maong and so on. And
eventually by the late 1970s, the
Chinese under Den Shopping decide to
open up their economy gradually very
very cautiously like lab experiments.
Okay. What lab experiments? Special
economic zones, SEZs. And this policy
was called the open door policy.
So
early 80s late 70s early 80s under then
shopping China created the first special
economic zones like Shenzhen Shenzhen is
very famous today right but they had
many of these more Xiaamin Shenzhen and
so on and in these special economic
zones which are like walled off from the
rest of the country essentially uh China
offered tax breaks and flexible labor
rules and significant autonomy to
investors to attract FDI foreign direct
investment And the objective was to over
over time create an export oriented
economy. So uh eventually in the mid 80s
uh this was extended to multiple port
cities. Eventually entire coastal belts
became you know sezz
and u some border areas like shenzhen
right border with Hong Kong. So these
parts of China became labs, laboratories
for market practices, for tech, for tech
transfer, for joint ventures with
foreigners and so on. And very rapidly
most of the FDI coming into China came
into the SZs. Okay. And uh uh so these
these special economic zones became hubs
for manufacturing for migration from
rural areas because people in rural
areas were until then farmers they
wanted to have a better life. They
wanted to have higher incomes. So they
would start they started migrating to
these special economic zones many of
these coastal cities and so on. And
eventually you had the rise of consumer
culture in China. And obviously you
would have inequalities. So the people
in these special economic zones became
wealthier than the rural Chinese and so
on. So it created inequalities in China.
But this brought China
uh into the global US-led system, the
global production networks, the global
supply chains and and so on. So that's
another big reform of the shopping.
Let's do let's do one more one more. The
one child policy transformative reform,
right? So this was social engineering.
Um so then shopping launches all these
major reforms right wants to transform
the economy but then he says that you
know the economy won't do so well unless
we restrain population growth. China's
population was already in excess of 1
billion or something right at the time.
So they needed to shopping decided we
have to restrain population growth.
Maybe the westerners put that in the in
his ears or whatever. So that's why he
instituted he instituted the one child
policy. The objective was to restrain
population growth. The objective was to
raise per capita income and per capita
resource availability. And these were
from Ding Shaing's perspective essential
to China's modernization.
Obviously, he's gone now and now China
is suffering the ill effects of the one
child policy, but it is what it is. You
know, he saw it as something that was
good for China. So, these are some of
the reforms that Ding Shaing produced
and rapid reforms. uh the rapid rapid
reforms had some unintended
consequences. There was inflation. There
were layoffs in various uh state-run
industries.
Corruption apparently those became
visible. You know, uh there was
inequality in income gaps among the
population of various parts of the
country. Uh eventually some people
became unhappy with this.
There were as as Chinese people be some
Chinese people became more prosperous
they started demanding political
liberalization democracy. It eventually
led to what happened in 1989, nationwide
protests in China, but it centered on
Tianman Square in Beijing, right? Where
students and u various other Chinese
citizens demanded uh you know political
reform, democracy, accountability,
anti-corruption, all that. And obviously
then shopping said that was too far that
they had gone too far and that's why
there was a military crackdown and one
party rule was preserved. So that's kind
of in a nutshell three of the major
reforms that Dingshop did. If I were to
go into all the reforms, I would have to
read a few books first of all and and
explaining all of that would take
several hours or maybe a whole semester
possibly if I was to do justice to it.
So that's kind of the kind of impact
then Xiaomi had on China. A
transformative figure for sure. He did
good, he did bad. Also the one child
policy is has in retrospect if you look
back from today's perspective it's it's
been a disaster for China but uh China
wouldn't be where it is today if Den
Shaing had not unleashed all those
reforms back in the day in the late '7s
and early 80s
right
Amisha says why didn't the Ottoman
Empire why didn't the Ottomans
assimilate Egypt and other such areas
into Turkish culture to what extent was
Turkish spoken in the Ottoman Empire
So Turkish first of all let us define
Turkish. There were various varieties of
Turkish. There were various Turkish
dialects.
So in various parts of what is now
Turkey you had various dialects and
various forms of Turkish or Turk
languages that were spoken. And there
was something called Ottoman Turkish
which was the Turkish language spoken in
the Ottoman court the court language.
And that was a mixture of Turic plus
Persian plus Arabic all combined
together into one new form of the
language called Ottoman Turkish which is
the origin mostly of today's Turkish
language.
So that was the Ottoman Turkish
language. Now when the Ottomans absorbed
all these other territories like Egypt,
like Syria, like Iraq, etc. into their
empire, they absorbed territories that
spoke different languages. So Egypt had
been ruled by the Mamblukes from the
from the 13th century all the way to the
16th century. It was in the 16th century
I believe if I'm not if I'm not mistaken
that the Ottomans captured conquered
Egypt. Uh Ottoman conquest of Egypt.
Ottoman conquest of Egypt 15 something
right? 1517
1517 okay so that's a 16th century the
Imaml sult it begins uh Mluk sultan of
Egypt is beginning 13th century right
13th century okay 1250 to 217 so 13th
century right so the Mluk sultanet had
thoroughly Islamized and Arabized Egypt
so by the time the Ottomans conquered
Egypt the Mluk sultan had been in power
for about 250 years more than 250 years
and Egypt was thoroughly Islamized and
Arabized. So the entire
society of Egypt spoke Arabic and the
leadership structure and the bureaucracy
and administrative structure of Egypt
was all done. All of it it spoke Arabic
and all of it was done in Arabic. So
what the Turks did is they did not
dismantle the existing existing
structures. They simply put a new layer
of of governance on top of that and that
top level governance was done in the
Turkish language. So Turkish became the
language of the elites of Egypt and
across the Ottoman Empire and they
allowed everything else to proceed in
whatever languages existed already
existed. So in Syria in in Iraq they
would have continued with those versions
of Arabic. when it comes to uh
going going westwards
when it came to uh what they called
Romelia which is the Balkan region the
Balkans where you have uh Serbia etc.
They allowed the local languages to
continue but all the local people they
had to when they interfaced with the
Ottoman Empire they had to do that in
the Turk uh Turkish Ottoman Turkish
language.
So during the Ottoman Empire's time
there were three major languages
essentially in the Ottoman Empire. The
language of empire and administration
and control and power was Ottoman
Turkish. The language of literature was
Persian
and the language of religion was Arabic.
And that's how it was in the Ottoman
Empire. The Ottomans never tried to
impose their language on the common
people. What they insisted on was the
religion. So they sought to unify their
empire through religion not language and
wherever they conquered they imposed the
the Islamic religion on the people. You
could see the effects of that in in the
Balkans also Albania and uh you know
Bosnia and so on. That's the legacy of
the Ottoman Empire.
Um so they and they had so many other
subjects you know they had the Armenians
who continued speaking Armenian. uh
there were the Kurds who continued
speaking Kuresh
and so on. So the Ottomans were not
imperialistic in ter in in in in the in
terms of language. They were
imperialistic in terms of religion and
they were okay with other languages
being spoken as long as the language of
command and control and administration
was Turkey. So that's how it was during
the Ottoman Empire and that's why Egypt
never became a Turkishspeaking nation.
Mohit Kashab says, "What exactly was the
1979 VA incident? While it remains
officially unexplained, many argue it
was a clandestine nuclear test that
confirmed Israel's status as a nuclear
power. What's the real story?" Well,
it's still officially unexplained. So,
what was this Va incident 1979?
In the 1970s the Americans set you know
launched a some a series of a set of
satellites and placed them these
satellites in earth orbit. The objective
of the satellites was to detect
clandestine nuclear tests or
noncllandistan nuclear tests. So nuc and
these satellites had a bunch of
instruments you know gamma ray detectors
and so on. It had the satellites had a
dete had an instrument called a bang
meter.
I'm not kidding here. Okay. Okay. Va
bang meter. Bang. Actual bang. Bang
meter. What's a bang meter?
A non-imag radiometer. U objective is to
detect atmospheric nuclear detonations
and determine the yield of the nuclear
weapon and then so on. The bhang meter
was invented blah blah blah destruction
description silicon photo diode sensors
and so on. The name of the detector is a
pun which was bestowed upon it by Fred
Reigns, one of the scientists working on
the project. The name is derived from
the Hindi word bhang, a locally grown
variety of cannabis which is smoked or
drunk drunk. Okay, we know what it is.
The joke being that one would have to be
high on drugs to believe that the bhang
meter detectors would work properly.
It's a bang meter, not a bang meter.
Okay, so that's the bang meter. Va bang
meter and the va incident we have on
Wikipedia.
So one of the instruments was a bang
meter and these satellites were launched
to detect nuclear explosions anywhere on
the surface of the planet. One of the
unintended consequences was that these
satellites started detecting things in
outer space things called gammaray
bursts. The most energetic explosions
anywhere in the universe. So this new
phenomenon was detected as an unintended
consequence by the VA satellites. But
that's astrophysics. Coming back to
geopolitics in 1979 between the southern
tip of Africa, South Africa and
Antarctica somewhere between this these
two regions one of the VA satellites
detected
the signature
of a nuclear detonation a double flash
event. So when a nuclear detonation
happens surface you know above
atmospheric nuclear explosion happens
there's a characteristic double flash.
The first flash is like a like a few
milliseconds long, very brief and very
energetic flash, mostly gamma rays and
also visible light, visible photons. And
then there's a secondary flash that
takes a few maybe a second or multiple
seconds. And that's an intensifying glow
and that's the secondary flash. That's
the characteristic of a of an
atmospheric nuclear explosion. This
double flash thing. And this wheeler
satellite in 1979 in this part of Africa
in of the Indian Ocean it detected this
characteristic double flash that's a
signature of a nuclear blast
and it is mostly assumed today that it
was an Israeli nuclear test done in
cooperation or collaboration with South
Africa because South Africa also had a
nuclear program of its own which was
dismantled um before uh apathide was
ended so that the South African nuclear
weapons don't end up in the hands of the
native population that sort of thing. So
that's why the nukes were dismantled and
you know given away to the powers that
be. Um so Israel also everyone knows has
this nuclear program. It's never been
officially acknowledged but everyone
knows Israel is an undeclared nuclear
state nuclear power with maybe 75 to 100
possibly uh nuclear warheads. So if you
want to have effective working nuclear
war whereas you need to test them and it
is said it is believed that Israel
conducted three nuclear tests in this
possibly in this in this area. What area
what region was this? Okay, we'll go to
Google this time and say VA incident
region. Okay. Uh VA incident
1939. Where did it happen? Let's see. I
um I'm say it's somewhere over here.
between uh South Africa and Antarctica.
Uh do we have a larger thing?
Okay, this red dot that's that's kind of
where it happened. Double flash near the
South African territory of Prince Edward
Islands in the Indian Ocean. So that is
the VA incident. the real story. We
nobody knows the real story, but it is
most likely that it was an Israeli
nuclear test uh done in collaboration
with South Africa most likely.
Amisha Mishra says, "How common were
Indian, East Indian from the
subcontinent that kind of slaves in the
US? What role did they play in American
society?" Well, there are very few
records of I'm not sure if there's any
records of Indian origin people who were
taken as slaves and they lived in the
US. Obviously, the British would have
sent some Indians also as slaves to the
to the Americas and probably to North
America also, but I'm not sure that any
records exist. But what's interesting is
that there is a record of u of an Indian
origin lady uh in New Spain which is
Mexico. Okay. The story of Katarina, the
San Juan. So, let's go to Google and
let's see the story of Katarina.
Katarina Desan Huan.
Okay.
She was known as China Pablana was an a
okay it's Asian now Indianborn woman who
was enslaved and brought to New Spain by
the Spanish East Indies and became
revered later as a saint in New Mexico.
The true origin is unclear but her
original name according to legend was
Mera. Mera and she belonged to a noble
family from India. She was born in6005.
He died in 1688
and you have uh various stories. Okay.
So an Indian noble woman was sold into
slavery and became a spiritual icon. She
eventually became a Christian saint
according to u this the legend and this
was the the house of this this lady this
Indian origin lady. So she eventually
became a sp a Christian saint
and uh she used to wear a sari
and she may have worn a different kind
of dress also a blouse and a pettic coat
and that perhaps
influenced the dress that you know
Mexican ladies wear possibly that's an
interesting story from from the Americas
you know this this Indian lady who was
enslaved and taken there and eventually
she would have been forced possibly
converted to Christianity and then she
became a Christian saint and ended up
being the inspiration for a dress worn
by Mexican ladies until the 19th
century. Katarina the son Juan that's
what was called her original name birth
name was most likely Mera Indian origin
lady enslaved
and transported to the Americas.
Okay,
real says how did marriages between
royalties transform alliances? Does this
way of transforming relations with a
with a foreign religion is it still
relevant? So let's take some examples.
Um the Gupta Vakatak age you had the
Gupta Empire and you had the Vakatak
dynasty kingdom in southern India region
of India and uh one of the great kings
of the Gupta Empire was Chundra Gupta II
of Samudra Gupta. Okay. So, Samudra
Gupta's son was Chandra Gupta II.
Chundra Gupta II had a daughter named
Prabhawati Gupta.
And Prabhawati Gupta,
she married
uh the king of the Vakatak. I forget the
name of the king. Rudra something,
right? Prahawati Gupta's husband.
Prabhawati
Gupta husband
Rudra Rudra the second of the Vakat
dynasty. So Prabhawati Gupta who is the
daughter of the Gupta emperor Chundra
Chundra Gupta II great Gupta emperor
okay whose empire was all the way from
the Chakshu axis river in central Asia
all the way to various parts of India
huge empire his daughter Prahawadi Gupta
marries Rudras the second Rudras II of
this of the of the of the Vakatak
dynasty.
Now she marries the guy and uh
within a few years he dies
and by this time Prabhawadi Gupta has
two young sons and one of them has to be
the future king of the Vakataks right
but they're too young so she has to be
the regent and she has to be the def
factor ruler until her sons are of age
so her husband dies young she becomes a
young widow she has got two young
children and her father obviously is
concerned about his daughter's
well-being and all that. Her father, the
emperor Chandra Gupti.
So, Chandra Gupta, her father visits
her, does makes the journey all the way
from his capital partly probably
whatever the capital was at the time and
comes and meets his daughter, offers her
some consolation and solace and whatever
and maybe starts a geopolitical
alliance. So what happens is that
prahavati Gupta then slowly becomes the
de facto ruler of the vakataks and this
makes the vakatak kingdom a de facto
vasal of the kupta empire. So the
marriage alliance transformed the whole
geopolitical equation. Right? That's one
example. Another example is the marriage
that is said to have happened between
Chandra Gupta Chandra Gupta Moria and
allegedly the marriage happened between
him and the daughter of Salucas Nicator
whatever her name was right so some
historians say this never happened some
say it happened I'm not sure what it is
but in case the marriage happened it was
the it is what what sealed the alliance
between India and Greece India and the
solucids so uh Alexander died after his
defeat in India he died in Babylon and
then his generals fought each other the
war of the diadokai
diadokai whatever it's called and then
Salucus negator one his best general
comes out victorious and and starts this
lucid empire and then he comes eastward
all over again and says hi to India by
by starting this short war with India
not a serious war and then the two you
know chandopa moria and salucas nik
probably meet and they shake hands and
chandupta accept Sucus's daughter in
marriage and then these two are no
longer enemies they are relatives and
that starts this long lasting alliance
of at least two three generations
between India and Greece India and the
solucid empire and as and
he tend gives Salucas negator a gift of
500 war elephants with which he
constructs a massive empire and he never
fights India after that so that's
another example of an alliance being
created through a marriage
And there are many other examples. The
marriage between uh
who was the husband of Katherine of
Braganza.
Okay, let's let's let's see this.
Katherine of Bragza, the Portuguese
princess.
Katherine of Braanza.
She married um Charles II of England.
And the dowy,
what was the dowy?
among other things the port of Bombay as
it was called at the time that's how the
British acquired Bombay of course it's
now Mumbai at that time it was called
Bombaya
Bombaya good Bay so yeah that's a
significant event in the British
occupation of India
many such examples can be you know
examined
says Why did civilizations like the
Roman Empire, India, and China have such
big problems with invading tribes?
Big civilizations
are by definition prosperous,
wealthy.
They have large quantities of resources,
large amounts of land, large numbers of
people, and lots of wealth. And when you
are a rag tag invading barbarian, what
do you seek? You seek plunder. You seek
wealth, you seek slaves,
you seek prestige.
So that's why these big civilizations
and empires, they draw invaders like
honey draws what? Bears, bees, whatever
that honey draws, right? So one good
example is the Hept Heptalite Empire.
The Heptalites, we called them the
Schwah Hunas, the white horns. And the
hepalites were attempting to invade
India at the same time when their their
people the Huns were invading Rome. The
Huns and the Heeptalites were
essentially the same people. The Sh the
descendants of the Shyu Shaunu who came
out of what is now Mongolia about 2,500
BC and set off a whole domino effect.
Eventually you had the heptoite empire
uh which which ruled a very large part
of central Asia and they kept on
knocking on India's door and our emperor
scandupta kept on repelling them over
and over and over again after he died
the doors broke down and the heptalites
came down south conquered Kashmir
conquered western India Gandhar
conquered Punjab subindu Gujarat
and they set up these hundik kingdoms
and they had some good kings and some
very nasty kings. Uh there there is
Torana, there is Mihir. Tormana was
okay. Mhir was very nasty allegedly at
least the Buddhists were not fans of
Mhirkul.
Uh and it is Mihir who's supposed to
have been the destructor of the Chashila
possibly. Um so India why why did the
Hoons keep on attempting to invade
India? Because India was so large, so
prosperous, they wanted to rule India.
Much better climate,
so much wealth. Similarly, the Huns also
did the same thing to Rome. Attela the
Horn, right? He crossed the Alps by
elephant. So, it's all about And when it
comes to China, well, China, the Mongols
obviously invaded China, but they did
not invade China for wealth. They
invaded China to teach China a lesson,
right? Ching Khan. So, different
reasons, but mainly is plunder. Jingis
Khan was never motivated by that. But
the Huns and whoever else, the Ostrogs
and the Vigotss and whoever else, they
were all motivated by blunder.
Okay, that brings me to the end of the
questions I have selected. Let's see
what we have going on the in the live
chat.
Okay. Okay, we have live chat going on.
I can see a lot of activity and I can I
can see 29 super chats. So, let us see
what we have in the super chats.
Football Bakt says what are your
thoughts on the warrior diet mentioned
in the Dhanurvea a high protein dairy
and low carb diet? Well, I haven't
studied the Danurvea. It's a part of
it's a component a sub sub section of
the atvid if I'm not mistaken
and
I am not 100% clear on the diet that
mentioned or may or may may be mentioned
in that what I do recall reading is that
it emphasized eating mansa which is meat
but obviously the clean mana means
you know fowl that's in that is birds
birds like like chicken obviously
chicken is an Indian bird and sheep and
goats not obviously cows or pigs so eat
meat there was an emphasis on ghee and
and milk and curd which is obviously
dairy and there was emphasis on on on on
legumes pulses like like like chana
hippies and and mung beans
what else and I suppose vegetables as
well sounds like a very yamna kind of
diet. The yamna had this sort of diet.
Meat and dairy mostly, right? Sounds
like that sort of diet if I recall
correctly. So that that obviously makes
sense. If you are warriors, if you are
physically active, you need a lot of
protein. You need you need u good
sources of of uh calories. You eat ghee,
you eat milk, I mean you consume milk,
you eat ghee um and you consume pulses
and all. It's going to give you protein,
carbohydrates,
and uh meat also obviously lots of
protein and fat as well. And ghee is
also, you know, high quality fat. So
that's that's a great diet. You know,
it's it's essentially
kind of like a ketogenic diet.
Obviously, if you eat pulses, the keto
part goes out of the window, but still
it's it's kind of a hybrid diet. Hybrid
as in
Indian and Yamna kind of diet. Yeah. All
right.
Gora TV says, "I have Hello, hello. I
have uploaded a video on my channel
regarding US's plan to contain China and
I've also included a snippet of your
analysis in it. I'd really appreciate it
if you could watch it and share your
feedback on it."
Okay. Um, I won't be able to do it right
now, but uh, I'll put that on my to-do
list. I'll check out your channel.
I'll watch your video and I'll I could
leave a comment
uh possibly. Um okay. So I'll not I'll
not do it right now, but okay. Thank you
for letting me know and I will look into
this. All right. And I'm glad that
you're doing something interesting and
something creative in this in this
manner. Uh great job for taking the
initiative and I will certainly check it
out. Good job.
The strummer is
the strummer says, "Can't the entire
world hypothetically come together to
thought thw thought US dominance and
bullying?" Well, hypothetically anything
is possible.
Can't Indians all unite together as one
culture, one civilization, one people?
Well, hypothetically we can. But look at
India today. Forget about the entire
world. We Indians are fighting among
each other,
right? So hypothetically, theoretically,
everything is possible.
But the real world is a messy place.
It's complicated and all these
theoretical things and hypothetical
things don't really work out properly in
the real world. The real world has a lot
of entropy and mess,
right? So all of this will happen if you
have the right leadership. Under the
light leadership, under the right
leadership, this can happen. But you
will need monumental leadership for for
that to happen. Even for India to come
together and to unite as one, you will
need monumental leadership. Leadership
that comes around maybe in once in 500
years.
Yeah.
Uh Chandra Gupta Mory comes one once in
500 years. Kaneshka comes once in 500
years. You know Samudra Gupta once in
500 years. Rajendra Chola once in 500
years once in 500 years that's the kind
of leadership we need right now for
India to come together today India today
is a nation divided right so
theoretically hypothetically this can
happen but in the real world it's very
difficult
explore world says why neuroscience
can't heal bipolar disorder I am not
aware of why it can't bipolar disorder
it's it's about yeah I'm not very
familiar with this
uh neuroscience.
So neuroscience is is a science of the
brain, right? Neurosurgery and all that.
Neuroscience, the understanding of the
brain, the different parts of the brain
and what what you know what parts of the
body they control and what they give
rise to and so on. And and bipolar
disorder is this disorder in which
people become hyperactive or something
is it hyperactive people and we don't
quite know how this how the mechanism
works. So yeah, because neuroscience has
has limitations, lots of limitations.
Um, the brain is a very poorly
understood organ. We understand the
heart very well. We understand the lungs
very well, the kidneys, the liver, the
spleen, the the the eyes, the retina,
the cornea, all of that we understand
pretty well. The brain is very poorly
understood. Very enigmatic organ. It's
the center of everything, isn't it? So
it's very poorly understood and that's
why probably neuroscience still can't uh
heal the bipolar disorder most likely.
Okay. Sam Kumar says
what will the world look like if China
replaces the USA? Well, we shall all be
speaking the different language. Yes, we
will all be speaking different language.
We speak Chinese. Chinese best language.
I'm sorry for that. Uh what will the
world look like if China replaces the
US? Well, it'll be aentric world.
Everybody the the the center of the
universe will become Beijing. Beijing
uh What's up China will say then I'm
sorry Xiinping
and uh it will it will be a Chinese
version of the world. Yeah everything
will be in Chinese.
Explore world says will Salman become
God after Galvin movie release? I have
no idea sir. I have no idea. I don't
watch Bollywood movies. So I can't even
remember the last Salman Khan movie I
watched. So must be decades that I've
seen seen one of those decades. I'm sure
I have no idea. That is not my my cup of
tea. I'm sorry. Pratik Shinoi says, "I
refuse to believe there's any country
without corruption. Yet some countries
still managed to succeed despite it."
Why is that? See,
there is no society without crime. Is
there a single society on the planet
where there is zero crime? No. It's
impossible. Why is that the case?
Because a certain percentage of the
human population has criminal
tendencies. Maybe one out of 100,000,
maybe whatever the the statistical
number is,
a certain small percentage of the
population has such tendencies. And
that's why in any population you're
going to have some crime. Of course, the
crime rates will vary. In India, we have
very less crime despite having almost no
police.
Yeah.
I mean, in in India, the police, what do
they do? They don't have machine guns,
right? They have lis at best. Go to some
other European countries, you'll see
police armed to the teeth. And still the
crime levels are so much higher. So, it
depends on the culture, society and all,
but every population has a certain
amount of crime. Similarly, every
population has a certain amount of
corruption.
So, it's it's natural. But some
countries deal with crime and corruption
better than other countries,
right? So, why do some countries still
manage to succeed despite it? Because
the leadership despises corruption and
they do everything to stamp it out. And
if they know they can't stamp it out,
but they can control it. They can keep
it under control and they can keep on
detecting and destroying it. They know
that new corruption will crop up here
and there. But they will again deal with
it. But in some countries hypothetically
corruption is the system itself and
everybody is is sharing the pie in some
countries wherever they may be. Maybe
some African countries or whatever. No,
I suppose. So that's the deal.
The chimp
the chimplo guy says biggest fans. Thank
you so much sir. uh if two countries
example Russia and India trade in a
certain currency example rupee to reduce
dependency over the dollar then how will
they manage the exchange rate?
How will they manage the exchange rate?
I suppose they will just go with the
existing exchange rates in the world
right now. See every both the ruble and
the rupee are free floating currencies
right? So whatever the current
international exchange rate is they will
go with that.
That's how it will be done. They will
not in the past it was different. In the
past India and and and and the USSR had
decided what the exchange rate would be.
It was a mutually decided thing. Today
it's not the case. Today it's free
floating. So each currency exact knows
exactly where it stands visa with the
other in the international market. So
that's how they manage the exchange
rate.
Sam the gamer says MIG 21 was good.
India failed on spares versus China's
J7. You know what? The MIG2 was a
fantastic aircraft.
It had to be retired because of factors
like metal fatigue and whatnot. The the
the airframes were very old 1950s
1960s60s probably airframes. Right? My
question is why didn't India produce
brand new MiG 21s in India with brand
new airframes and brand new engines?
I'm sure the the Soviets gave us the
blueprints.
We simply didn't care for doing these
things.
We could have reverse engineered the
engines and whatnot of the Mig 21 and
then made small iterative improvements
and come up with our own enhanced
version of the MIG 2021
and started our own families of jet
fighters. We even had the Marut.
So the Mig21 was an outstanding fighter
plane. It was the best fighter plane of
its time. The Americans were frightened
of it. Even until the 2010s and 2020s,
it was still a pretty potent fighter
plane, right? So, it is India's failure.
India's lack of vision, lack of
ambition, lack of leadership.
We could have taken that jet forward. We
could have improved upon it. We could
have built our own increasingly improved
versions and iterations of the Mig 21.
We simply didn't care to do it. India. I
don't know what sort of leadership and
everything we have. I just don't know
what to say really.
Lakshman
Tahiliani says, "Can we vaselize our
neighbors? Regime change other means?"
No, we are simply not powerful enough.
Like I explained a couple of times at
least in this live stream, we can't. We
aren't powerful enough. The US is way
more powerful than India in the
subcontinent itself. And it's see the US
is more powerful than China. in China's
backyard. That's why China can't take
Taiwan. China can't vilize Taiwan
because the US is too powerful in
China's backyard. Russia has to fight
Ukraine because the US is powerful in
Russia's own backyard. The the US is the
superpower, right? That's why we can't
vaselize our neighbors.
Godliness says US hedgemony is on the
rise. World except for China to some
extent including India is a is following
the US design. All the talks of
ddollarization, multipolar world seem
immature and Trump still has three years
ddollarization.
Uh yeah, multipolarity
what what other master stroke vishwaguru
superpower all the stuff. Yeah. See the
US is the ultimate hedgeim. It is the
only superpower. Now we are seeing very
clearly the limitations of Chinese power
and Russian power. Talking about Indian
power, the US has never been as powerful
as it it is right now.
And you can see that they are running
rough shot over the western hemisphere
and
twisting the arms of various nations
across the world outside of the western
hemisphere. They're arm twisting India
right now with with respect to the
economic deal with respect to Russian
oil and so many other things.
They are they are squeezing China.
They're cutting off China's sources of
energy, aren't they? Russia is the one
nation that is a hard retaliator and
Russia is the one standing up to the US.
China is playing the economic game and
the resource game, but China is not
standing up to the US militarily,
right? The ddollarization and all. Well,
eventually the world will move on to the
dollar. That will happen,
but it's not some master stroke that is
already pre-planned 20 years in advance
and all that nonsense. Okay. So let's be
mature. Let's be realistic. Let's live
in the real world. Let's talk stop
talking about vishwaguru and master
stroke and all that. Okay. I am very
optimistic about India despite all the
problems we face. I
it is likely that India may become a
vasal in the next 5 years but hopefully
not. The likelihood is higher than 50%.
But hopefully not. So let's be
optimistic and hopefully India prevails.
Let's see. But let's be realistic and
not let's not talk about master strokes
and god knows what else all the time or
ever
godliness says based on your critical
evaluation of the current geopolitical
dynamics. What all historical events you
feel will repeat themselves in the
future. All historical events will
repeat.
Okay. I mean all classes or or all
categories of historical events will
repeat over and over again but maybe
with the advancements in technology the
the geopolitical repercussions and
ramifications will be much more violent.
So what kind of historical events
happen? We have the rise and fall of
empires. When an empire falls, it's
chaos. It's chaos for decades or even a
couple of centuries, right? uh when you
also have things like the susides trap
where you have an existing hegemonic
power which is faced with the pro
prospect of a rising hegemonic power war
is inevitable
so that's what we are seeing right now
in the world we are seeing the thusid
trap being managed by the US and China
the war is happening but it's a
geoeconomic war right now it's not a
military war China can't stand up to the
US no chance
so all these things will play out over
and over again. There are various kinds
of you know rivalries that happen.
So all the events that that have
happened in the past will happen over
and over again in the current
geopolitical scenario the in the future
scenarios as well in the context of the
technologies of the time.
Sam the gamer says Ukraine war frozen.
Is Russia isolated? Ukraine war is kind
of a
war of attrition right now. A frozen
conflict, long war scenario. You know
these
these terms I have used so many times
because of the way things are going. Um
is Russia isolated? Well, Russia has
it depends on China. China also depends
on Russia more now increasingly. Uh
Russia is significantly isolated but not
entirely isolated. A lot will depend on
India's approach. Now India is under
increasing American pressure to stop
buying Russian oil. If that happens if
India bends the knee in from that
perspective in that in that particular
scenario then Russia will get a little
more isolated and a little more
dependent on China. China is also
getting isolated.
So the Americans are trying to bring
Russia and China together and then the
great great master stroke game plan is
to offer Russia way out of the Ukraine
war. But the condition is stop selling
oil to China.
So that's where we're going possibly.
Sana Tani Dwanch says are gourjashatrias
are gourj and gjur and kusans related. I
suppose some gurj are chhatrias. Today
the guruja people they exist on both
sides of the India Pakistan border. In
the Pakistani side there are gurj
muslims. On the Indian side there are
Gurjar and Gujar Hindus and the Guruja
people gave gave rise to Gujarat as
well. Are the gujars and the Kushans
related? Possibly. I mean there are no
Kushans today but millions of people in
India will have Kushan ancestry. Little
bit little bit. So possibly Gujarat and
Kushans may be related. We're not quite
sure. The Kushans eventually just merged
into the Indian population. assimilated
into the Indian population just like the
Yavanas and the the Shakas the Skithians
right and the Hunas afterwards
all these uh
late entrance into India they all just
harmoniously assimilated into Indian
society so it's possible that there are
millions maybe tens maybe hundreds of
millions of people in India who have
Kushan ancestry yavana ancestryan
ancestry huna ancestry little bit little
bit but you can't say who will
So uh can't say for sure if the Gujars
are direct descendants of of Kushans or
not. Can't say for sure.
Kishant Bordoy says happy Valentine's
Day to everyone.
All right, sir. Happy Valentine's Day to
you as well.
Stick life says USD isn't assetbacked,
but neither are most currencies. Any
nation can print money out of thin air
within its own territory. What's your
opinion? Well, you can do that, but that
has immediate repercussions on your
economy. If you simply print a whole
bunch of money out of thin air, it's
going to cause and and and you put that
money into circulation, it's going to
cause immediate inflation.
Immediate inflation.
The value of a currency goes down. You
don't want that. You don't want that,
right? Anybody can do that, but nobody
is stupid enough to do that. The
Americans do it, but they do it in a way
that that puts all the owners and
pressure on the rest of the world. The
rest of the world pays for the money
that Americans print for themselves.
They have rigged the game, the
Americans, right? And that's why
everyone wants to move away from the
dollar slowly, gradually, quietly, still
whatever.
So the US dollar isn't assetbacked. It
is nuclear weapons backed and military
backed. And that is a very valuable
backing to have. Other currencies, what
backing do they have? Right. Um today
there's no currency that is pegged to
the price of gold. The ruble was kind of
for a while
after 2022. Uh but no no um currency is
actually peg pe pe pe pe pe pe pe pe pe
pe pe pe pe pe pe pe pe pe pe pegged to
the price of gold today. I mean that
would make it a very valuable currency.
It would make it a proxy for gold but
it's not the case. So the point is any
nation can do this but it will be
devastating for their economy. That's
why nations don't do that.
Sagni Kachara says, "Your views on Nikil
Gupta pleading guilty for Kalistthani
panun murder plot in the US. Is it a
defeat for the US?
How will this impact India US
relations?" Uh, yet to be seen. I
haven't really analyzed this new
development. Nikil Gupta some some guy
um has plead guilty for conspiring to
murder this uh American terrorist panon,
right? Gur Patran Singh Panon. Um is it
a defeat for the US? Is it a bad thing
for India? I'm not sure at this point in
time. I have not examined the situation.
And uh who is this Nikil Gupta by the
way?
I'm not even sure who he is exactly. So
yeah, it's it's it's it's a emerging
story, developing story. So maybe day
after tomorrow when we do the next live
stream, I may be better informed about
it. Right now I'm not really sure.
Uh Yuk says, "Is India's AI summit AI
impact summit good? Is it worth going?"
I am not sure. I mean I hear that all
the top players are coming right. So I
suppose it will be worth going if you
are in the field of AI to understand
what's happening what where the world is
going and what India's uh relevance in
the world of AI is going to be. If if
this affects you if you are part of the
thing if you if this is your domain your
territory your field then it makes sense
for for you to go go there. Yeah.
IPK1s says sir nothing just wanted to
say sir
all right sir thank you all right h
really miss really now miss patel says
what if US vasals are secretly biting
time too they must loathe being under
the thumb also realizing today's
realities are grim for India in it you
see
let's say you are a US vasal it means
you are a nation let's say as a European
nation Okay. And you are a US vasal.
Do does that nation loathe being under
the US thumb?
If a nation is a US vasal, it means
their leadership is completely aligned
with the US which means that their
leadership has incentives
to keep being on the US side because it
it puts money in their pockets. So they
will not loathe being under the thumb.
When it comes to the population of the
nation, they they may not even know that
there is something called vasalhood.
They may even not know that the US
actually controls their nation. There
are various ways of keeping people
oblivious to these matters. For example,
Japan. Most people in Japan have no
understanding of the fact that Japan is
a US vasal and under US permanent
military occupation. They think it's an
agreement between the two nations and
the Americans are are they have 130
military bases in Japan to safeguard
Japan. That's what they may believe and
they may have been told in the education
system that Japan is an evil nation with
an evil culture and that's why Japan
must never militarize. They may actually
believe this and they may think that the
Americans are the great civiliz
today that the British came to India to
civilize us. Right? So most nations are
not even aware of these matters.
Uh yeah, realizing today's realities are
grim for India. Well, not terribly grim
but yeah
times are tough but hey
it is what it is. We'll deal with it
right let us not be discouraged. Miss
Patel
Ray Narayan Singh says I am a GC general
general category person and blackbilled
by what's happening with us but it feels
feels good that some like me Ajit barti
de talks etc have Indian spirits still
thanks in love we must never give up
uh what's happening isn't isn't
the right thing clearly you know I have
always had from the first ask lie I I've
always had the same message, a message
of unity.
We Indians must unite.
But there are forces in India that seek
to divide us by creating this these
divisions.
You know, you know what they say, a
permanent solution to a temporary
problem becomes a permanent problem. And
sometimes people try to create solutions
to problems that don't even exist.
And this entire matter of cast and all
will annihilate cast right no you want
to perpetuate cast. So there is a big
problem with our politicians
and uh it's a big issue. They seek to
divide India further clearly
and that's very unfortunate and we need
to rise above this. You see the problem
is that
a lot of these divisions have been
created over over the centuries and it
has created this situation in India
where you have different classes or
categories of people who have differing
interests.
A number of people will have shared
interests which will be which will be
you know diametrically opposite in some
cases to the shared interests of a
different group of people. If you are a
great leader, you have to ensure that
you engineer a situation where everybody
has the same interests instead of
dividing the nation further. So that's
kind of where we are today. This is this
is why I keep saying India is still
deeply deeply colonized. The entire
system is a colonial system and the
system will strengthen itself against us
against our civilization and that's
where we are stuck right now in India
and that's what we all have to push back
against
push back in a civilized legal manner.
So um let us not be
uh let's let's stay optimistic I would
say.
Okay. Okay, dark side of the moon says
you say AIT is fake. Uh Arian Arian
invasion theory is fake. I am a techie
beginner in this field. I want to
research myself. What steps, fields,
papers, data did you follow to reach to
the conclusion. I'll give you my article
I wrote in 2016 2017. You can start from
there. I've got given all the sources,
resources, right?
Yan invasion
myth Java.
Uh sorry. Okay. So you can go to this
medium article. Okay,
just search for the Arian invasion myth
Abijit Cha. That's it. All all you have
to search for. So it is an article I
wrote in May May 14th, 2017 and it's a
pretty long article in which I've gone
into the entire thing. I've put out all
the evidence. Okay, obviously this is a
9-year-old article. So some of the
things may need updation, but it still
is very very relevant and valid. And I
have given a bunch of references as
well. Okay, a bunch of references. You
can check out those references. There
are links and references
and yeah, you can start from this and
then you can take your own journey
wherever the rabbit hole uh leads you.
All right, sir. Dark side of the moon.
All the best. I'm glad that you are
interested in this in this field. You're
a techie. So you you you may have uh
technical knowledge scientific uh in a
scientific bent of mind that will help
you understand this better. All right
sir all the best.
Vicki Khana says why ironically many
Hindus on X trads bureaucratic announce
like
like Iran of ayati. If Dharma people
plus military plus bureaucrats plus anon
plus common people come together, can
they bring revolution and system like
Iran?
Um
do a lot of Indians like
Kame is Iran?
I I don't know about that. If dharmic
people in military and bureaucrats and
anons and common people come together.
Listen for all kinds of people to come
together you need leadership really
really strong leadership
because otherwise people have their own
interests right to bring people together
takes uncommon leadership to show them a
path in which
uniting is the better option and having
shared interest is a better option.
It's not like
You know like 75 cats will not
voluntarily come together right somebody
has to bring them together Indians are
like cats
Indians are also like sheep I mean
Indians have this superp position of cat
sheep thing
yeah so Indians Hindus especially they
simply won't unite that's very cat-like
behavior cats will never move in herds
cats are always solitary creatures right
but Indians and Hindus also have this
sheeplike behavior. So, Hindus are a
super superp position of cats and sheep.
But anyway, that's a that's a segue into
something else. Um, yeah, Dharmic people
see Dharmic people have their own
interests. Military people have a
different set of interests. The interest
of the nation poss hopefully.
Bureaucrats have a different set of
interests. Anons, well, they are
anonymous. We don't know who they are.
Common people, well, common people, how
do you define common people? So all
these different groups of people, sets
of people have possibly different
interests. Some of these may intersect,
many of these may not inter intersect.
So how do you bring them together? You
need high quality leadership for that to
happen.
Where is that leadership? That's the
question.
Okay. ICMBB says, how has Paris
maintained some autonomy unlike UK?
Paris has maintained some autonomy. Oh
yeah, Paris. Okay. How has France
maintained some autonomy from the US
unlike the UK? Well, first of all,
France is not under US military
occupation.
Unlike most other European nations,
France isn't. Secondly, France has its
own indigenous nuclear deterrent
which is and the nuclear warheads that
France has are indigenous. They are made
by France and they are mated to
Frenchmade missiles, ICM, ICBMs,
right? Third,
the delivery systems, the submarines are
also French-based are also French,
indigenous. The French have their own
fighter planes, their own um their own
jet engines, their own aircraft
carriers. Everything is indigenous.
Because of these reasons, the French
have autonomy. They're qu they have a
quasa independent foreign policy. Not
entirely independent but quasa
independent right that's the reason why
because they have they are atman
that's why
angad gal says do you think deep chopra
and Stephen hawking were involved in
those cruel things and why is America
rejecting Indian vizak because I see so
India hate okay um
look Deepak Chopra seems to be an
absolute hypocrite
a scum of a person clearly
right I mean the kind of emails sent to
Jeffrey Epstein. I would not even want
to read them here.
Which clearly indicates that he was
involved. He was he was neck deep in all
kinds of murky activities. And the murky
activities on Epstein island can only
mean one thing, right? Disgusting,
monstrous behavior.
So yeah, probably Chopra Deepak Chopra
was involved in these matters. He
portrays himself as a spiritual guru.
uh peddling um dismantled and digested
Hinduism, Hindu spirituality to the
Americans while being a Christian
himself. So Deepak Chopra
scummy person Stephen Hawking I I don't
know about him. Was he also involved in
cruel stuff? I mean he was not capable
of doing cruel stuff but who knows who
knows I don't know physically he was
incapable because he was paralyzed but
then he was there and he seemed to be
pleased apparently. So I have no idea
man really why is America rejecting
Indian visa?
I'm not sure America is re rejecting
Indian visas. It's it's it's difficult
for Indians to get American visas but I
don't see blanket rejections happening.
I think wait times are very long and so
on but u yeah it's it's um I don't see a
policy of rejecting Indian visas. For
example they banned Pakistanis and
Bangladeshes from getting American visas
but not Indians. So it's not quite the
case. India hate. Yeah. When you grow as
a nation, when you rise as as a nation,
you're going to have hate. Of course.
Soldier boy says, "Was the Datlo of Pass
incident USSR experiment or what was
it?" Uh we don't know what it was. Huge
mystery. Diatlo of Pass incident. You
know this this a group of hikers that
went into the this forest in the winter
was frozen all over, snowing everywhere.
and they went on this on this excursion
in the hills or whatever in the in the
forest for days and then they
disappeared
and then their bodies were discovered in
in the tents all frozen and all I don't
know some had massive injuries and they
all look scared and frightened and some
looked like they had fallen from the sky
or something. So we don't know what
happened. Nobody knows maybe UFOs maybe
aliens maybe maybe military experiment
we don't know still a big mystery and
they made movies about that I think with
aliens or whatever. So that's in the
1960s or something like long ago the
atlas incident USSR
Vicki Khana says in Pakistan there are
the the majority are GC Muslims general
category Muslims Rajputs Jats Jats Jats
Cindis Kayasts Brahmans amazing to
observe but why Mujaher's general
categories migrated when heart money
legacy invested in UP Delhi and bond
with Hindu general category I I'm I
don't know why these muhajes migrated
there. Maybe they thought that they're
getting a nation for their own religion
and they don't want to live with Hindus.
I suppose maybe. Yeah. Um obviously
these people who migrated to Pakistan
would have left behind their homes and
lands and whatnot. You know, wherever up
they live, wherever.
Why did they move there? I I'm pretty
sure it's mainly religious reasons.
Mainly religious reasons. Maybe Jana was
was able to inspire them all to leave
everything behind and move to this new
country, new land, new artificial
temporary country.
Um in Pakistan the majority are are the
majority
uh general category Muslims, Rajputs,
Jads,
um Brahmans, a lot of these Pakistani
military folks are converted Rajputs.
Well, if you're converted, you are no
longer a Rajput. By the way, to be a to
be a Rajput, you need to have a kulvi.
If you're converted, you no longer have
one. So, you can't be called a Rajput
anymore, I suppose. And same with
Brahmans and whoever else, right? If you
no longer worship, I mean, continue your
your your traditions, then you are no
longer part of the original uh whatever
categories you were part of, I suppose.
But whatever, the Pakistanis are still
proud of their their pre-Islamic
heritage, Rajut, whatever. Come on, man.
Uh so I'm not sure why they migrated.
Most likely would have been religious
reasons.
Agam Senpai says in the 2026 interim
frame India cuts tariffs to 0% while US
keeps 18%. China maintains strict
reciprocity. Does this asymmetry risk
over sovereignty potential vasal route
or a calculated trade-off? See clearly
the tra the the agreement this framework
interim framework is not an equal
um balanced framework clearly the US has
the upper hand but so does the US with
every other partner if you look at um
okay let's let's let's try and see this
okay um
what tariffs has US imposed on imposed
on
on South Korea, Japan. Um, what about
France,
uh, Germany,
Germany,
uh, what about Indonesia? Let's see what
tariffs.
So, um, this is from when? This is from
a long time ago, August 25. So, okay,
this is obviously not recent. So, this
is okay. So, it's not recent. Do we have
something 2026 overview? Okay. Trump
tariff tracker.
So, let's see.
Uh, this is not
okay. Afghanistan 15%, Algeria 30%,
Angola 15%, Argentina 10% baseline.
Well, well, well. Bangladesh 20%.
Bolivia 15, Bosnia 30, Botswana
15, Brazil 10 40%.
Uh, BRICS 10%, Brunai 25, Cambodia 19%,
Cameroon 15%, Canada, uh, Fentinel Trans
Shipment. Oh, huge on Canada. Uh, China
34%, Fentinel 10%, all kinds of other
things as well.
uh Denmark 10 + 25 or 10 or 25, Ecuador
10%, El Salvador 10%, small European
Unions additional threatened 50%,
alcohol 200% and so on. So as you can
see this is a this is
a litany of of arm twisting over all
these nations. Iraq 35%, Israel 15%,
Italy
uh to be determined. Indonesia 19%
Japanif okay Japan is a vasal 15%
Kazakan 25% so as you can see
as you can see nowhere do you see equal
treatment nowhere do you see actual
reciprocity the US is the most powerful
economic entity in the world and they
will do whatever they want there's
nothing other nations can do so they are
now asking to pay for the privilege to
the American markets
you can't expect strict reciprocity with
a nation like the Yes, the world has
changed. The days of 3 to 5% UF US
tariffs are gone, long gone. So this is
not something that uh that uh risks our
sovereignty. This is not something that
can potentially make India wasal. This
is simply a recognition of the fact that
we have an unequal inequalation
which is simply a fact. Okay? So it's
it's fine. It's not an issue. I know a
lot of people are crying about this and
complaining about this, but let's be
realistic. No other nation has proper
that sort of balanced relationship with
the US. It's unequal every time.
Uh Suraj Kandel says any enterprise in
India capable of making a jet engine.
I'm not I don't know.
I suppose the the the new partnership we
have with Safa the French manufacturer
will give us a jet engine. I suppose
hopefully DRDO can make jet engines but
not the ones not powerful enough for the
for for full scale fighter planes good
enough for drones and so on. So yeah
that's where we are.
Okay. Amisha says in history did most
people just not know their age.
I suppose it depends on the context. If
you were living in an established
advanced civilization maybe India maybe
Egypt maybe Mesopotamia maybe China. I
suppose most people would have known
their age, right? If you lived in in a
civilization where you had advanced
timekeeping systems and advanced
calendars like in India, I think most
and and where you had be high levels of
prosperity and education, I suppose most
people would have known their age. But
if you were if you belong to the hept
hepilit kingdom, heptite the huna
kingdom, most h nomads would perhaps not
know their age. I suppose if you were a
Viking warrior, maybe you would not know
your age. If you were a Roman citizen in
Rome, I suppose you would know your age.
If you were in Egyptian citizen, unless
you were a slave, you probably would
know your age. So, it depends on the
context and all. Yeah.
Nurak Singh says, "Is the new Bangladesh
government beneficial for India or is it
no or if not is Rorow failed again?"
by what row failed again.
What roof again?
Bangladesh is now East Pakistan.
Bangladesh is ruled and controlled by
the US whether you realize it or not.
The election that happened in Bangladesh
was not a free and fair election. The
most prominent political party,
the Awami League was not allowed to
contest the election. It's a rigged
election. And if this new guy has won
Tariq Raman has won, it means he has
been allowed to win by the US and he's
going to be beneficial for the US.
I don't see this equation changing much.
Okay. And it's not raw failed again.
It's not the case at all. The draw has
failed. It is simply uh the recognition
of the fact that the US is more powerful
than India even in the subcontinent. It
is just a just a fact of life.
Giora TV says India is replacing MIG 21s
with pages mirages and MIG 29s with
Rafas and possibly Sukoy 30 with Suko 57
in the future. What about Jaguars in is
the world in general dumping ground
attack fighters? I'm not sure. I'm not
sure. Um
the Sukoy 30s will last a long time uh
at least a couple of couple of decades.
uh if we do go for the Sukoy 57
eventually we could use the existing
Sukoy 30 production lines or assembly
lines to produce the Sukoy 57s in India
possibly depending on the size of the
agreement we we reach with Russia in
case we are going to let's say
hypothetically we need 200 Suko 57s in
that case we should set up production
lines in India so we could use the
existing Sukoy 30 infrastructure for
that yeah uh MIG21s are being replaced
with pages. Yeah, Mirage is in Mig 29ths
with Rafals. I think the Miragees still
have a few years in them. Mig 29ths too
maybe a decade at least. So it's not
like we are now going to decommission
the Miragees and Mig 29s and get the
Rafals. No, we're going to operate all
these aircraft together because we have
a significant shortfall of the numbers
of fighter planes we need to have, we
ought to have, right? So mid29s
definitely are being replaced with the
theas if we can produce the you can't
produce the fighter planes without jet
engines. The Americans are not supplying
jet engines or they're supplying like
three engines a year, right? They're
choking off India's pages assembly
lines, manufacturing lines, the
Americans deliberately, they want
Pakistan to become more powerful than
India in terms of air force uh strength.
Um yeah, I don't know about jaguars.
Is the world in general dumping ground
attack fighters? I am not sure about
that. Jaguars, I don't know what the
situation is. Are we dumping the
jaguars? I'm not sure we are. How many
jaguars do we have? I I don't think
they're dumping the Jaguars. We will
continue to operate those as well.
Deepakati says from my previous
question, changed username from the
chimplok guy is was difficult. Okay,
actually I wanted to know about exchange
rates will be connected to the US dollar
eventually. Look, the entire global
system is connected to the US dollar,
right? And every currency which is free
floating has a relative exchange rate
with respect to the dollar and every
other currency. So it's kind of in a in
a in an in a mathematical equilibrium.
So uh your exchange rate depends on your
relationship with the dollar as well as
your relationship with the ruble. So if
you if let's say a currency
has the exchange rate of 10 to1 versus
dollar which means $1 is 10 units of
your currency
and let's say the ruble has an exchange
rate of 20 rubles to this US dollar.
then I suppose your currency one unit
will be equal to two rubles right that
that's how it works relatively
um so yes the exchange rates will indeed
be connected to the US dollar but the
but if two countries are are are
transacting their business without the
US dollar then the US dollar will not be
involved even if the currencies are
connected
in terms of exchange rates with the
But the transaction is going to bypass
the use which is what ideally our
nations want.
Skylight says you may want to check out
old compass an Indian history channel. I
believe he made a one to one scale of an
indust.
Okay I shall. Interesting. I shall I
shall check it out. Thank you very much
for the recommendation. Old compass.
Old compass. Okay. Thank you. Vihung
Kuran says was H Marut actually a decent
indigenous fighter jet had India been in
a better position today if that project
mature matured further the H Marut was
an outstanding fighter jet it was
designed by the German designer Kurt
Tank okay let's let's see who Kurt Tank
was
Kurt Kurt Tank sorry Kurt Tank
So he was a German aeronautical engineer
and test pilot. He led the design
development at Faulk Wolf from 1931 to
45. He created several luvaf aircraft
like the wolf fighter jet
outstanding fighter plane uh the
wolf and so on. So he was an outstanding
designer. Okay. And then he designed the
Marut, the H Marut.
Uh and the Marut was an outstanding
fighter plane. Okay. The only issue the
Marut faced was that it had underpowered
jet engines which was not a problem with
the plane. It was a problem with the
engine. If India had acquired high
powered jet engines, the the Marut would
have been probably one of the best
fighter planes in the world. and Indian
politicians killed off the Marut. If we
had continued the Marut, if we had
iteratively improved upon it, we would
have been one of the foremost
uh
nations with fighter planes today. We
would have had possibly multiple
families of fighter planes. So, our
politicians killed off this fantastic
fighter jet program. Fantastic, isn't
it?
Uh RB368
thank you very much indeed sir. Thank
you.
A Rahul says similarities between
ancient canadite religion and Norse Vic
Hinduism Bal Bilsbub is in no absolutely
not.
Can Catholics called bal devil devil
during crusades
the
see bal the word bal means lord or
master.
So you can have multiple gods with the
epithet of Bal. Epithet of Bal. You had
Bal Ammon. Bal something else as well.
Okay. So
Bal Hammon. Okay. Bal Hammon
which means Lord Hammon.
Lord Hammon. Uh Bal
Bal something else as well. Bal Hadad
Bal Hadad. So you have multiple gods
with the epithet epithet of Bal. Okay?
It's not one s single god and the bil
zebub is bal zebub isn't it the lord of
the flies or whatever it is. How can
that sort of god be Indra? There's no
similarity between there's no connection
between the canonite religion and
indo-uropean religions. Nothing
whatsoever.
Sam the gamer says why endless delays
it's impacting Awax refueler. I have no
idea.
I'm not aware of the situation. Sorry.
D Kat says Stephven Hawkings paralysis
did not impact every body part. I equate
Kumar Roy says, "Did you see the Bal
statue burning in Iran?" Really? I'm not
aware of this. Let me see quickly.
A bow statue burning
in
what is this?
Burned in Iran. Really? When did this
happen?
Okay. I was not aware of this. And uh
Okay. Interesting. Are the Iranians
saying that Bal is a Israeli god? Not
sure about that, but okay.
Uh RB368
says, "Any thoughts on Cecil Roads?
Roots is secret global secret roundt
organizations peddling globalist
propaganda since the early 20th century.
I'm not aware of this.
Look, um Cecil Roads was this uh the guy
who essentially colonized Africa on
behalf of the British, right? There are
these roads scholarships that are still
offered in his name.
Uh so yeah I'm aware of that much and
he's one of the great evil colonizers of
Africa. We know that slave owner and all
that slave trader and u yeah but I'm not
aware of the global secret roundt
organizations peddling globalist
propaganda since the earliest 20th
century. I'm not aware of that. Sorry.
Pratip Kumar Roy says about Freemasons.
I recently found out a masonic temple
near my house. It was built in the
1870s. about Freemasons.
Once again, I'm not very very very very
uh
very aware of of their history kind of
begins in obscurity. They seem to be
connected possibly with the Knights
Templar
and uh they have been persecuted at
times. I think Napoleon or the French
banned Freemasons.
Freemasonry is banned in some countries
in the world. It's quite open in other
countries.
Uh what are their objectives? Who are
they? What are their origins? I am not
100% sure about that. I've not really
studied the history. Um there's a
masonic temple near your house. Well,
that's interesting. 1870s.
Okay. Interesting. I believe that
multiple famous prominent Indians were
Freemasons.
You can look up their names and there
exist freemason uh grand lodges or
whatever masonic temples or whatever in
India as well today. So yeah that much I
know but I don't I'm not aware of their
origin story and history and their
agenda
and objectives. Soldier boy says who
were deenisans?
Why did they go extinct? Why do naza
mummies have three fingers which is
intact found eggs inside their abdomen
like reptiles? I'm not sure about the
Nazca mummies. Um whether it's a hoax,
whether it's a real thing, looks pretty
real from whatever little I've seen
about that. The tridactyl creatures. Why
do they have three fingers? I have no
idea why they have three three fingers.
Were they
native to Earth or were they aliens who
died on Earth or if they are real or are
they fantastic fabricated hoaxes? I'm
not sure about that. Uh who are the
Deniso ones? They were one of the
subspecies of of human beings.
So we are homo sapiens. Our cousins were
homo neianderthalisanderthalis
and we also had homo denisova or
whatever it's called. So that was
another closely related subspecies of
human beings.
And today homo sapiens depending on
where you are some homo sapiens some
some humans today have some denisovven
ancestry which means that we intermixed
interbred with them. Some some homo
sapiens did that. Uh who were they? They
lived in urasia. Um the first ever
evidence of them was found in Denisova
cave in Russia in Siberia I believe. Uh
some evidence of them fossil evidence
has been found in Tibet. So clearly
these people lived in Eurasia. There
were some species of humans our cousins
and they eventually died out. I don't
know why they went extinct. Maybe did we
do that? I mean it is said that we made
the Neanderthalss extinct.
Maybe even Denisans. Maybe we are very
aggressive as a species. I don't know.
Could be Pratep Kumar Roy says about
Happy Science Japan. They have sent us
in India too. That's another cult is it
I've heard. I'm not sure. Happy Science.
I don't know if it's a cult or it's just
a nice thing but centers in India. Okay.
Interesting. Uh Pratip Roy says I found
out that most of the reformists like Ram
Mohandro, Viveandanda Motilu Dehu were
freemasons. Are we controlled by them?
Sar joined politics.
Yeah, I'm not sure about the Ram Moy but
Vive Khan and Muti Mutilu were
definitely free Freemasons. At least
that's what the website claims. Okay. Um
India
India freemasons.
So Grand Lodge of India whatever that is
and if you go there if you open their
website I hope it opens someday. And
what is this?
Okay, so there is Viveandanda
and who else have been great Freemasons
of India? I don't know who these
fantastic gentlemen are but okay.
Uh who are the historical Indian
Freemasons?
Do we have something? Do we have a
history about us? Grand past
Grandmasters etc etc. Oh Shri Ratan Tata
Ji Tata Rady Kipling. Who else? Who
else? Who else? Swami Viveananda. Who
else? Let's go.
Uh Motilal Naru Jar. So some of these
people as you can see u yeah pretty
prominent Indians. I'm not sure about uh
Mr. Ram Muhan Roy but definitely Swami
Vivean and the Motilu were free business
at least that's what the website claims.
Are we controlled by them? I have no
idea. Join politics. Thank you very much
for the suggestion sir. T2 says thoughts
on thought on Bahaj
painted gray wear preodiscript
I'm not sure about that something that
some news coming out of Egypt is that
what you're referring to I haven't seen
that yet so I too early for me to
comment
says will India have to will India have
to surrender shina now
why just because some new guy comes to
power in Dhaka doesn't mean
surrender really no we don't have to do
that don't worry about that
pratipar says about new world order I
don't know about renew world order sir I
don't know about that
they say it's a conspiracy theory I mean
if you yeah so I don't know about that
T2 says your thoughts on Iran's fellow
cemetery 3000 BC I don't know about this
either and I am reluctant to open that
search
query on Google. So I shall not do that
here. I I'm not aware of this. I'll
check it out. Sounds
interesting perhaps. Not sure. Anyway,
thank you. Okay, so that brings me to
the end of today's live stream. All the
questions are done. Thank you very much
as always. Great fun. Okay, we have one
more super chat. Uh, Freemasonry was
founded by Francis Bacon, English guy.
Francis Bacon.
Well, I've heard
stories of
of some kind of connection with the the
Knights Templar, you know, back from the
days of the Crusades. That's almost like
900 years ago, thousand years ago. Um,
the Knights Templar were eventually all
executed, right? And they left something
there was some connection apparently,
which may or may not be true. Okay.
Vehav Sharma has a question. How Arctic
TH aggravates climate concerns and
ignite geopolitical competition? how
India strengthens its digital fraud
resilience. I don't know about digital
fraud resilience but the Arctic Thalate
becomes warmer then more ice across the
world will melt.
So let's say the the global temperature
rises by an average of 2°C.
So it means that some amount of the ice
which is not the extreme pools
will melt because of rising temperatures
right and some of that will happen in
the arctic regions. That's what's that
is what's believed
and we know that glaciers are receding
and so on. So the arctic regions of the
planet which two were always you know
icebound throughout the year they will
now start opening up for uh for shipping
and uh commercial traffic and
exploitation of resources and all that.
So what that could do is it could uh
raise
uh sea levels globally potentially
swallow up countries like the Maldives
and and you know cause problems in
Bangladesh
and because of this this Arctic region
opens up for shipping and commercial
exploitation there will be competition
in that region for resources between
major nations like Russia, the US and
China. China is a near Arctic nation and
so on. So that's how it could ignite
geopolitical competition. Okay.
Pratipar Roy says about film Eyes Wide
Shut 1999. The film showed some secret
masonic rituals. The director Stanley
Cubri died a few days later. Warner
Brothers Productions. I have heard of
this story. Stanley Cub Cubri did die a
few days after he finished the movie.
And uh the movie I think I saw it back
in the day pretty
Yeah.
And um yeah, all those masks and stuff
and some rituals, maybe masonic rituals.
Um at that time it was a much younger
me. I did not understand much about it.
Maybe if I see it now again I may have a
different perspective on it but I have
not seen it in a long long time. So
yeah, it's about secret societies and
secret rituals and whatnot. Some kind of
underlying message as well. Yes, you're
right. Tom Cruz, Nikol Kidman who were I
suppose married at the time.
Okay, so that brings me to the final
conclusion of this live stream. Thank
you very much everybody. Thank you for
the questions. I look forward to seeing
you on Monday 8:00 p.m. for the next
live stream. It was supposed to be
tomorrow but tomorrow there's a cricket
match India Pakistan. Nobody will turn
up for my live stream. So I'm doing it
on Monday 8:00 p.m. I look forward to
seeing you there at that time. Take care
everybody. Thank you so much for your
viewership for your questions. Keep
asking questions. Keep learning. Keep
raising your standards. I shall see you
in the next one very soon. Take care.
Good night. Good day. Bye-bye for now.